<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The golden treatise of the auncient and learned father Vincentius Lirinensis. For the antiquitie, and vniuersalitie, of the Catholicke religion: against the prophane nouelties of all heresies: newly translated into English by A.P. Verie profitable for all such as desire in these dangerous times, to imbrace the true Gospell of Iesus Christ, and to remaine free from all infectio[n] of false doctrine as in the preface more at large is declared</title>
            <title>Pro catholicae fidei antiquitate libellus. English</title>
            <author>Vincent, of Lérins, Saint, d. ca. 450.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14430</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24748</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119131</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854338</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854338</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19754</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14430)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19754)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 368:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The golden treatise of the auncient and learned father Vincentius Lirinensis. For the antiquitie, and vniuersalitie, of the Catholicke religion: against the prophane nouelties of all heresies: newly translated into English by A.P. Verie profitable for all such as desire in these dangerous times, to imbrace the true Gospell of Iesus Christ, and to remaine free from all infectio[n] of false doctrine as in the preface more at large is declared</title>
                  <title>Pro catholicae fidei antiquitate libellus. English</title>
                  <author>Vincent, of Lérins, Saint, d. ca. 450.</author>
                  <author>A. P., fl. 1596.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 110 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Fr. Garnet's second press] With priuiledge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1596?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Pro catholicae fidei antiquitate libellus.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer supplied and publication place and date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19754:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>Judgment.</head>
                  <p>SAint <hi>Jerom</hi> ſaid, <hi>Whatſoever he did he ſtill thought that that Voice was ſtill in his Ears, Ariſe ye Dead, and come to Judgment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Jerom</hi> uſed this excellent ſaying, <hi>If my Father ſtood Weeping on his Knees before me, and my Mother hanging on my Neck behind me, and all my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Siſters, Children, and Friends howling on every ſide, to retain me in a ſinful Life, I would run over my Father, fling my Mother to the Ground, deſpiſe my Kindred and fling them under my Feet, that I may run to</hi> CHRIST. Heres Love and Fortitude!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CHriſoſtom</hi> ſays, God had rather Men ſhould love him, than fear him; to be called Father, rather than Maſter: He wins by Mercy, that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not periſh by Juſtice.</p>
                  <p>O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Godly Man knows how to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of Mercies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19754:2"/>
                  <p>It was St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s ſaying, <hi>Dead Fleſh is to be cut off for fear of Gangrene.</hi> Arias <hi>at firſt was but a Spark, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not ſuppreſſed betimes, proved the Incendary of the whole Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Love is ſtrong as Death; as Death killeth the Body, ſo Love of Eternal Life kills Worldly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and Affections.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> being predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant in the Soul, deadens the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to any thing elſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> asked <hi>Peter</hi> Three Times, <hi>Loveſt thou me,</hi> not for his own Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, but that by his Threefold Profeſſion he might help his Three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Negation of him. <hi>Nicephorus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Good and Wicked Men, and Hypocrites.</head>
                     <p>THey are like True and Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Money, the one ſeems to be good, and is not; the other both ſeems and is good. <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19754:63"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith, <hi>As a Rock, tho' the Winds blow, and the Waves beat againſt it, is Immovable; ſo</hi> Faith, <hi>grounded on the Rock</hi> Chriſt, <hi>holds out in all Temptations, and Spiritual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chryſologus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Neither in the Steel alone, nor in the Flint alone, any Fire can be ſeen, nor Extracted, but by Conjunction and Colliſion; ſo, nor by</hi> Faith <hi>alone, nor by Works alone is Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to be attained, but by ioyning both together.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Hales</hi> ſaith, <hi>What the Eye is to the Body, Faith is to the Soul, it's good for direction if it be kept well. And as Flies hurt the Eyes, ſo little Sins, and Ill-Thoughts do the Soul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Divine Love</hi> (ſays <hi>Baſil) is a never failing Treaſure; he that hath it is Rich, and he that wanteth it is Poor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> ſaith, <hi>A Bulwark of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damant is not more impregnable than the</hi> Love <hi>of Brethren.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19754:1"/>
                  <p>THE GOLDEN TREATISE OF THE AVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIENT AND LEARNED FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther VINCENTIVS <hi>Lirinenſis.</hi> For the antiquitie, and vniuerſalitie, of the Catholicke Religion: againſt the prophane nouelties of all Hereſies: <hi>Newly tranſlated into Engliſh by A. P.</hi> Verie profitable for all ſuch as deſire in theſe dangerous times, to imbrace the true Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, and to remaine free from all infectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of falſe doctrine as in the Preface more at large is declared.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                     <body>
                        <p>
                           <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                           <hi>With Priuiledge.</hi> ⸪</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19754:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader zelous of truth, and deſirous of Saluation: A. P. wiſheth the knowledge of the one in this life, and the fruition of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the life to come.</head>
                  <p>IPRESENT thee heere (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) the auncient french Father <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius Lirinenſis,</hi> attired after the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh cutt: a booke as learned as litle, and no leſſe profitable, then pleaſant: of ſmalle volume, if thou reſpect the quantitie, but of rare priſe if thon con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider the qualitie. It intreateth not of gathering &amp; ſcraping togither the pelf of this world, which choaketh vp the <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. V. 22 <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. V. 24</note> heauenly ſeed of Gods word, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth man in a dangerous ſtate, if we cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dite him who being rich, for our ſake became poore: it diſputeth not of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious and gallant attire, nor of the art
<pb facs="tcp:19754:3"/> of pampering this corruptible carcaſe which brought that braue belligod, of <note place="margin">Luc. 16</note> whome we read in the Goſpell, to the furious flames and endleſſe tormentes of Hell fire: it proſecuteth not wicked and wanton diſcourſes, which corrupt good manners, being in very deed the bellowes to kindle the coles of carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, the nources of vnchaſte thoughts, and the very baite with which the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill doth daily angle and catch the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate ſoules of mortall men. But it handleth that which redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to the benefite of our ſoule, created to the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God, and ſheweth vs the way how we may ſo gouerne this fraile veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of ours, in the tempeſtious Sea of this wicked world, that at laſt we may ſafely arriue at the porte and harbour of celeſtiall felicitie. For if the firſt ſtep to Heauen is to beleeue aright, and the foundation and ground of all ſaluation be faith, as I thinke no man can doubt, that beleeueth that there is any God or truth at all, then can not this golden treatiſe but be acceptable to all ſuch as loue Ieſus Chriſt, and tender the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:19754:3"/> of their owne ſoules, beeing as it were the heauenlye piller of fire that <note place="margin">Exod. 13</note> may guide vs through the deſerte of this world, vnto the land of promiſe, and the glittering ſtarre to leade vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Mat. 2</note> the new borne King of the Iewes &amp; Sauiour of mankind. But to the end that thou maiſt more plainly &amp; particulerly view the excellencie &amp; great neceſſitie of this rare booke, and as it were with Moiſes from the toppe of Mount <hi>Nebo</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 34.</note> contemplate the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with milke &amp; honie. I will briefly ſet downe ſuch motiues as inuited me to the labour of the tranſlation, for the ſelfe ſame, as I verily thinke, cannot but inflame thee to the dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reading of the ſame. Three principall reaſons then eſpeciallye moued me. The firſt was, becauſe it is very auncient, being written aboue an eleue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hundred yeres paſt, for it was compoſed three yeeres after the generall Councell of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> as appeareth in the concluſion of the booke. And as the Author him ſelfe is of greate antiquitie ſo is his doctrine more auncient, beeing the ſelfe ſame
<pb facs="tcp:19754:4"/> which floriſhed in his time, and came from the Apoſtles of CHRIST: which thing as it was neuer of any good man doubted of, ſo is it alſo moſt apparant: Firſt by ſound reaſon grounded in gods word, becauſe when any man writeth ought concerning faith and religion, and the ſame is not controld of any of that time, it is an euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t argument, that it was conſonant to the doctrine then generally taught and receaued, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thoſe Paſtors and Doctors which God (as S. Paul ſaieth) <hi>hath giuen that we be not litle ones wauering and be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about with euery blaſt of doctrine,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4</note> could neuer haue held their peace, but would as the Prophete admoniſheth <hi>Haue cried out, exalted their voice like</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eſa. 58.</note> 
                     <hi>a trumpet,</hi> as we finde in like caſe, the licentious <hi>Nicholaits</hi> noted by S. Iohn for their falſe doctrine: <hi>Himineus</hi> and <note place="margin">Apoc. 2</note> 
                     <hi>Philetus</hi> reproued by S. PAVL for an error about the reſurrection. Secondly <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> becauſe the author him ſelfe doth not only confeſſe the ſame, in ſetting down the anſwere of many excellent holy, &amp; learned men, which liued in his daies,
<pb facs="tcp:19754:4"/> nor only becauſe he acknoledgeth that what he hath here written, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued it from his aunceſtors, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, both which he doth in the very firſt entrance, and generally through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the wholle booke: but eſpecially for that towardes the latter end he ſo highly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth the generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> that is the Parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the world: which ſurely he neuer wold haue done, had he not ioined with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in opinion, concerning faith and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and what their opinion was, him ſelfe recordeth, for he ſaith that thoſe Fathers inſpired by God decreed that nothing was to be beleeued, but that which the ſacred antiquitie of our fore fathers agreeing togither in Chriſt, had holden and beleeued: Which ſurely is a notable argument, that what faith was by Chriſt planted, and his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples preached, was by them carefully kept and maintained: which thing is eſpecially of vs Engliſh men to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted becauſe the firſt foure generall Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cells, amongſt which this of <hi>Epheſus</hi> is one, and the third in order, are worthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:19754:5"/> allowed by acte of Parlament. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore moued with ſuch reaſons, we may <note place="margin">Anno. 1. Elizabe.</note> without all ſcruple or doubt, not only read this booke but alſo imbrace and intertaine it, as the common doctrine of that time, as the religion practiſed &amp; reuerenced in the primatiue Church as the faith and beleefe of the <hi>Epheſin</hi> Councell and ſo conſequently, as the true doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt. Now the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeeing we liue in thoſe daies in which ſo many new ſectes and doctrines, ſuch ſtrange and monſtrous opinions, ſuch ſuperſtitious and new-fangled deuiſes flie vp and downe the world, and ſeing wee are fallen into the latter times in which <hi>Men ſhall heape vp to them ſelues maſters according to their owne deſires,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4</note> 
                     <hi>and ſhall not indure ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d doctrine, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert their eares fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truth &amp; be conuerted to fables.</hi> In which <hi>they ſhall loue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>more then God, haue a ſhew of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, but yet denying the vertue therof,</hi> In which <hi>many ſcoffers ſhall come, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ep. Iud.</note> 
                     <hi>according to their owne deſires, who deuide them ſelues, ſenſuall, not hauing the ſpirit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19754:5"/>
                  <p>In which <hi>many falſe Chriſts, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe and ſeduce</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 24</note> 
                     <hi>many.</hi> Very neceſſary it is, being thus fore-warned of God, that before all thinges we take great heed not to be peruerted, and ſeduced by erroneous teachers, or falſe Prophetes, but on the contrarie doe diligentlye preſerue our faith, the light of our ſoules: the roote and foundation of all goodnes, &amp; with out <hi>which it is impoſſible to pleaſe God</hi> as S. PAVL ſaith. Wherin we can take no <note place="margin">Heb. 11</note> better courſe, no way more ſurer then to repaire to the time of the primatiue Church, when the blood of Chriſt was yet freſh bleeding in mens harts, when the Goſpell was inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly preached, firm<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly beleeued, ſincerely practiſed, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by miracles, eſtabliſhed by the death of ſo many thouſands of Martirs eſpecially being exhorted hereunto by the holy ſcriptures, for as by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are admoniſhed of the daungers and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the latter daies, ſo are we for a preſeruatiue againſt them, ſent to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times to conduct vs to gods true religion. <hi>Stand</hi> (ſaith the Prophet Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie <note place="margin">Cap. 6.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19754:6"/> 
                     <hi>vpon the way and inquire of the auncient pathes, which is a good way and walke in that and you ſhall finde reſt for your ſelues.</hi> Salomon likewiſe in his pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerbes admoniſheth vs in this ſort. <hi>Do not paſſe the auncient boundes which thy</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Cap. 22.</note> 
                     <hi>Fathers haue ſet downe.</hi> And in Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticus. <hi>Do not ſet light by the report of thy elders for they haue learned of the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Cap. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>forefathers, becauſe of them ſhalt thou learne vnderſtanding, and in the time of neceſſitie ſhalt thou giue anſwere.</hi> To the end therfore (gentle Reader) that thou be not caried away with the ſweet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictions of thoſe licentious maſters, with which the latter times, according to the predictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Apoſtles, ſhould be much peſtered, nor ſeduced with the erroneous doctrine of thoſe falſe Prophetes, and falſe Chriſtes, of which the ſonne of God, the true Prophet &amp; true Chriſt, hath forewarned vs. And that thou maiſt find out a good way to walke in, and keepe thee within the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient boundes, ſet downe by our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, and by their report learne wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and vnderſtanding: I am to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt
<pb facs="tcp:19754:6"/> thee to vouchſafe the reading of this olde Father newly tranſlated, and I nothing doubt but thou wilt geue that cenſure which Queene <hi>Saba</hi> gaue of <note place="margin">3. Reg. 10.</note> the wiſdome of <hi>Salomon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond reaſon which ſet me for ward was, for that I finde this booke, not written againſt ſome one or a few perticuler falſe teachers (as <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> and diuers auncient learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors did againſt the <hi>Arians, Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and ſuch like) but againſt any he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie or erroneous doctrine whatſoeuer which is a thing of ſo great importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as I knowe not what can be deuiſed more. What golde were to much, or what treaſures to deare for that medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine which had vertue to cure all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes? Falſe doctrine and hereſie is a greate ſoare, a canker more peſtilent then any corporall infirmitie whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, ſeing this worketh only the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall diſtruction of our carcaſe: but that cauſeth death both of bodie and ſoule euerlaſting. In other bookes we find the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſome ſpeciall faſe point of doctrine, in many the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw
<pb facs="tcp:19754:7"/> of diuerſe, but to deſtroy all at one blow, and thoſe each ſo contrary to them ſelues, ſo diſtinct for time, ſo diuerſe for place, ſo many for number, is a propertie peculiar only to this moſt excellent treatiſe, and therfore it may fitly be compared to that miraculous pond, wherof we read in the Goſpell, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioan.</hi> 5</note> which cured all diſeaſes: for as that wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter moued by the Angell cured what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer infirmity of him that firſt entred in: ſo this booke writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no dout by the motion of the holy Ghoſt, hath force to cure any ſuch as is corrupted with erroneous doctrine, or to preſerue him from all infection, if he voutſafe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in, that is to read it to ponder it, and to waigh diligently what is ſaid an diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of. The reaſon why this booke hath this rare qualitie, in my opinion is, becauſe it ſheweth the right way of expownding Gods diuine ſcripture, in which ſo many to the great daunger of mens ſoules, doe ſo greatly go a ſtray: and therfore as <hi>Dauid</hi> ouerthrowing <hi>Golias</hi> the cheefe cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pion of the camp, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 17.</note> put all the <hi>Philiſtians</hi> to flight, ſo no
<pb facs="tcp:19754:7"/> maruell though this auncient Author diſcouering the falſe expoſitions and gloſes of ſacred ſcripture, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall piller of all poiſoned doctrine ouer throweth alſo all wicked hereſie.</p>
                  <p>The third and laſt motiue which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged me to this labour, and ought partly to moue thee to the reading, is the breuitie of the worke, the finenes of the methode, the eloquence of the ſtile: and therfore if long and large vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes do litle pleaſe, this is ſhort which can not cauſe diſlike, if confuſion be ingratfull, a methodicall order can not but like thee, if a ſtile harſh and courſe fitteth not thy taſte, then I truſte that which is fine, pleaſant &amp; delicate will content thy humor. Only I am to craue pardon that my rough &amp; rude Engliſh, nothing aunſwereth his ſmoothe and curious latin, and therfore I could wiſh thee, if ſkill ſerueth, rather to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon and parle with the Author him ſelfe, then to vſe the helpe of his rude inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretor, otherwiſe for ſuch as be not of ſo deepe reading, for whom eſpecially I haue taken this paine, I am to deſire
<pb facs="tcp:19754:8"/> that they nothing diſlike the ſoueraign medicine for the wodden box, nor the exquiſit and rare gemme for the courſe casket.</p>
                  <p>Theſe be the reaſons (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) which eſpecially moued me to the tranſlating of this auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and learned Father: I beſeech thee as thou tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt the ſaluation of thine owne ſoule, that thou wouldeſt voutſafe to reade him attentiuely, in whom thou ſhalte ſee cleerelye as in a glaſſe the faith of our forefathers, the religion of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue Church, and in him thou ſhalt finde by Gods word and authoritie of ſacred ſcripture, the madnes of all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes cruſhed in peeces, and that in a ſhort methodicall, and eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. The holy Ghoſt which moued no doubt this auncient learned Father to the writing of this worke, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline &amp; moue thy hart to the diligent reading and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere folowing of the ſame.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>A. P.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19754:8"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>INCENTIVS LIRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis for the Antiquitie and Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalitie of the Catholicke faith, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the prophane Nouelties of all Hereſies.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE holy ſcripture of GOD ſaying and warning vs in this ſorte: <hi>Aske thy Fathers and they ſhall tell thee, thy elders</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 52</note> 
                     <hi>and they ſhall report vnto thee:</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Accommodate thy eares to the workes of wiſe men:</hi> Likewiſe <hi>My ſonne</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prou.</hi> 22 <hi>Prou.</hi> 3.</note> 
                     <hi>forget not theſe ſpeeches but let thy hart keepe my wordes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It ſeemeth vnto me a peregram and the leaſt of Gods ſeruantes, that it ſhall by his gratious helpe be a matter of no ſmall profitte to ſet downe in writing what I haue of holy Fathers faithfully receaued, being a thing very neceſſary for mine owne infirmitie, hauing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies therby in readines, how by dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19754:9"/> reading therof I may helpe my weak memory. Vnto which labour not only the profite to be reaped by the worke, but alſo the very conſideration of the time, and opportunitie of the place mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued and inuited me: the time, becauſe reaſon it is, that ſeing it conſumeth and bereueth vs of all humane and earthly thinges, that we ſhould alſo take out of it ſomething which may auaile vs to life euerlaſting: eſpecially ſeing the ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rible iudgement of God, which we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect drawing neere vpon vs, doth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly inuite &amp; prouoke vs to increaſe our ſtudies and exerciſes in religion, and the fraudulent dealing of new He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes requireth much care and atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The place, becauſe hauing forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the company and troubles of the world and choſen a ſolitarie Abbey in a litle towne for mine abiding where I may without any great diſtraction of mind put in practiſe that which is ſong in the Pſalme: <hi>Be vacant and ſee that I am God.</hi> With which reaſons alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordeth the purpoſed end and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">Pſa. 45</note> of my whole ſtate of life, in that I
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19754:9"/> haue by the helpe of Chriſt, after long &amp; diuers ſtormes indured in the warres ſhrewded my ſelfe in the harbour of a religious life (a ſecure port for all ſtates of men) where contemning the blaſtes of vanitie and pride, I may pacifie god with the ſacrifice of humilitie, and ſo eſcape not only the ſhipwracke of this preſent life, but alſo the fire of the next.</p>
                  <p>But now in the name of God will I ſet vpon that, which I haue taken in hand, that is, to ſet downe in writing ſuch thinges as our forefathers haue de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liuered and committed to our charge, vſing herein rather the fidelitie of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter, then the preſumption of an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, meaning yet to keepe this rule in my writing, not copiouſly to lay forth all, but briefly to handle each neceſſary point, neither that in fine and exacte wordes, but in eaſie and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſpeach in ſuch ſort that moſt things may ſeme rather touched then declared. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> write delicately and penne curiouſly, which truſting either vppon witte, or moued with reſpect of dewty, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe any ſuch actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but for me it is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19754:10"/> that for helping my memory or rather forgetfulnes I haue gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither this Commonitorie, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding by Gods grace I will dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeuour by litle and little (calling to mind ſuch thinges as in times paſt I haue learned) to correcte and make more perfect. And this haue I thought good to forewarne, that if haplye this worke of mine paſſing forth, fall into the handes of Cenſurers, they do not ouerhaſtely in it reprehend that which they vnderſtand preſent promiſe to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, with future correction better to poliſh and amend.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                     <p>INQVIRING therefore often with great deſire, and attention, of very many excellent, holy, &amp; learned men, how and by what meanes I might aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly and as it were by ſome generall and ordinary way diſcerne the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholicke faith, from falſe and wicked Hereſie. To this queſtion I had vſually
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19754:10"/> this anſwere of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all, that whether I or any other deſired to finde out the <note place="margin">Note the anſvvere of many excellent holy and learned men.</note> fraud of Heretickes, daily ſpringing vp and to eſcape their ſnares, &amp; willingly would continue ſafe and ſound in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he ought two maner of waies by Gods aſſiſtance to defend and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue his faith, that is firſt by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the law of God: ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly by the tradition of the Catholicke Church.</p>
                     <p>Here ſome man perhaps may aske, that ſeing the Canon of the ſcripture is perfect &amp; moſt aboundantly of it ſelfe ſufficient for all thinges, what need we ioine vnto it the autoritie of the church her vederſtanding and interpretation. The reaſon is this, becauſe the ſcripture being of it ſelfe ſo deepe and profound all men do not vnderſtand it in one and the ſame ſence, but diuers men diuerſly this man and that man, this way &amp; that way expound and interpret the ſayings therof, ſo that to ones thinking, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men, ſo many opinions almoſt may be gathered out of them, for <hi>Nouatus</hi> expoundeth it one way, <hi>Photinus</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Sabellius</hi> after this ſort, <hi>Donatus</hi>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19754:11"/> after that: <hi>Arius, Eunomius, Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> will haue this expoſition: <hi>Appoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naris</hi> and <hi>Priſcillian</hi> will haue that: <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinian, Pelagius, Celeſtius,</hi> gather this ſence, and to conclude <hi>Neſtorius</hi> fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out that, and therfore very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary it is for the auoiding of ſo greate windings and turnings of diuers errors that the line of expounding the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes and Apoſtles, be directed and drawen, according to the rule of the eccleſiaſticall &amp; Catholicke ſence.</p>
                     <p>Againe in the Catholicke Church, we haue greatly to conſider, that we hold that, which hath bene beleeued euery where, alwaies and of all men: for that is truely and properly Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke (as the very force and nature of the word doth declare, which compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth all thinges that be truely vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall) and that ſhall we do, if we fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vniuerſalitie, antiquitie, conſent. Vniuerſalitie ſhall we folow thus, if we profeſſe that one faith to be true which the Church throughout the world ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth and confeſſeth: Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhall we follow, if we diſagree not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19754:11"/> any whit in opinion from them, whom all know that our holy elders and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers reuerenced and had in great eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. Conſent ſhall we likewiſe fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, if amongeſt our forefathers we hold the definitions and opinions of all or almoſt of all the Prieſts and Doctors together.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                     <p>VVHAT then ſhall a Chriſtian Chatholicke doe, if ſome ſmall part of the Church cut it ſelfe off from the communion of the vniuerſall faith? What elſe but preferre the helth of the wholle body before the peſtife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and corrupt member. what if ſome new infection goeth about to currupt not onlye a litle parte but the Wholle CHVRCH? Then likewiſe ſhall hee regarde, and be ſure to cleaue vnto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, which cannot poſſibly be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by any craftye noueltye. What if in antiquitye it ſelfe, and amongeſt the auncient fathers, be founde ſome error of two or three men; or haplie of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19754:12"/> ſome one citie or Prouince? Then ſhall he diligently take heed that he preferr the decrees and determinations of the vniuerſall auncient Church, before the temerity or folly of a few. What if ſome ſuch caſe happen where no ſuch thing can be founde? Then ſhall be labour, by conferring and laying together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt them ſelues the auncient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers opinions, not of all, but of thoſe only which liuing at diuers times, and ſundry places, yet remaining in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and faith of one Catholicke Church, were probable maſters and guides to be folowed: and whatſoeuer he perceiueth, not one or two, but all iointly with one full conſent, plainly vſually, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly, to haue holden, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, &amp; taught, let him know that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ſcruple or doubt he ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, hold, &amp; profeſſe that faith, that doctrine, that religion. But for more perſpicuitie &amp; light of that which hath bene ſaid: ech part is to be made cleere with ſeuerall examples, and ſomewhat more at large to be amplified, leaſt to much breuity breed obſcurity, &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19754:12"/> haſte in ſpech take away the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and waight of the matter.</p>
                     <p>When in th time of <hi>Donatus,</hi> of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> came the <hi>Donatiſtes,</hi> a great part of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricke</hi> fell headlong into his furious er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and vnmindfull of her name, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and profeſſion, preferred the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious temeritie of one man, before the Church of Chriſt, then all thoſe of <hi>Africke</hi> which deteſted that prophane Schiſme and vnited them ſelues to the vniuerſall Churches of the world, they only amongſt them all remaining with in the boſome of the catholick Church could be ſaued, leauing certainly a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table example to their poſteritie how euer after by good cuſtome the ſound doctrine of all men, ought to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the madneſſe of one or a few. Likewiſe when the hereſie of the <hi>Arians</hi> had neere corrupted not a litle parte, but well nigh the wholle world, in ſuch ſort that (almoſt all the Biſhops of the latin Church deceaued, partly by force partly by fraud) mens minds were couered as it were with a miſt, what eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in ſo great a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was to be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19754:13"/> folowed: then whoſoeuer was a louer and a folower of Chriſt, and preferred auncient faith before new errour, was not touched with any ſpott of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. The daunger of which time doth aboundantly ſhew, what calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie entereth in, when a new doctrine is admitted. For at that time not onely ſmall matters, but thinges of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce were ouerthrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for not only alliance, kinred, frends, families, but al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo cities, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthes, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinces, yea &amp; at length the wholle Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Empire, was ſhaken &amp; ouertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prophane noueltie of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> like a certaine Bellona or furie, had firſt taken captiue the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, afterward ſubduing all pallaces to her new lawes neuer ceaſed after that to trouble and confound all things pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and publicke, holy and not holy, putting no differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwixt good and truth but as it were from an high place did ſtrike all at her pleaſure. Then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried women were defiled, widowes ſpoiled, virgins violated, Abbeis ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, Cleargie men vexed, Deacons
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19754:13"/> beaten, Preiſtes baniſhed, Dungeons, Priſons, Mines, filled with holy men, of which the greater part baniſhed the citie, like exuls, pined and conſumed away amongeſt deſertes, dennes, and wilde beaſtes, with nakednes, thirſt, and hunger. And all this miſerie had it any other begining? but becauſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was admitted for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly doctrine, well grounded antiqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, ſubuerted by wicked noueltie, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſt our Superiours decrees were vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, our Fathers ordinances broken, the Cannons of our aunceſtors abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and whileſt the licentious libertie of prophane and new curioſitie, kept not it ſelfe within the chaſte limittes of ſacred and ſound antiquitie. But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps we deuiſe all this of hatred to No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueltie, &amp; affection to Antiquitie? Who ſo thinketh, at leaſt let him geue cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to bleſſed <hi>Ambroſe</hi> who in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond booke to <hi>Gratian</hi> the Emperour bewailinge the ſharpe perſecution of that time, ſaith thus: <hi>But now O God</hi> (quoth he) <hi>we haue ſufficiently waſhed and purged with our ruine and blood, the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19754:14"/> death of the Confeſſors, the baniſhment of Preiſtes, and the wickednes of ſo great impiety, it hath manifeſtly appeared that they cannot be ſafe which haue violated and forſaken their faith.</hi> Likewiſe in his third booke of the ſame worke. <hi>Lett vs therfore</hi> (quoth he) <hi>keepe the precepts of our elders &amp; not with temerity of rude preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, violate thoſe ſeales deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to vs by inheritance. None durſt ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that propheticall booke cloſe ſealed, not the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, not the powers not the Angells, not the Archangelles: to explicate and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret that hooke was a prerogatiue only reſerued to Chriſt. The Preiſtlike booke ſealed by the Confeſſors and conſecrated with the death of many Martirs, which of vs dare preſume to open, which booke ſuch as were compelled to vnſeale, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding afterward when the fraud was condemned, they ſealed againe, they which durſt not violate or touch it becam Martirs: how can we deny their faith, whoſe victorie we ſo praiſe &amp; commend?</hi> We commend them I ſay O venerable <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> we ſurely commend them, and with praiſes admire the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For who
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19754:14"/> is ſo ſenſeleſſe, that although he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ariue to their perfection, deſireth not yet to imitate them, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no force coulde remoue from defending theire aunceſtors faith: not threatnings, not flatterings, not life, not death, not the King, not the Emperor, not the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, not men, not Deuills, thoſe I ſay whome for maintenance of religiouſe antiquitie, our Lord vouchſafed of ſo highlye and ſo greate a grace, that by them he would repaire the ouerthrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Churches, geue life to the dead ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie, reſtore the ouerthrowne glory of Preiſtes, blotte out &amp; waſh away with a fountaine of heauenly teares (which God put into the harts of the Biſhops) thoſe wicked, not bookes, but blottes &amp; blurres, of new impiety, finally to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore almoſt the wholle world (ſhaken with the cruell tempeſt of vpſtart here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie) to the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t faith, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> new error, to olde ſobernes, from new madneſſe, to auncient light, from new darkeneſſe. But in this diuine vertew which they ſhewed in the confeſſion of their faith, this thing is eſpecially of vs to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19754:15"/> that in that antiquitie of the church they tooke vpon them not the defence of any one part, but of the wholle. For it was not lawfull that ſuch excelent &amp; famous men, ſhould maintaine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend with ſo great might &amp; maine the erroneous ſuſpitions, and thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary each to other, of one or two men or ſhould ſtand in contention for the temararious conſpiracie of ſome ſmall Prouince, but they did thoſe by folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Canons and decrees of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke and Apoſtolicke veritie of all the Preiſtes of holy Church, rather to betray them ſelues, then the vniuerſall auncient faith. For which fact of theirs they merited ſo great glorie that they are accounted not only Confeſſors but alſo iuſtly and worthely the Princes of all Confeſſors. Great therfore &amp; ſurely diuine was the example of theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Confeſſors, and of euery true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke continually to be remembred who like the ſeuenfold Candleſticke, ſhining with the ſeuenfold giftes of the holy Ghoſt, deliuered vnto all poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie a moſt notable example; how after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19754:15"/> in each fooliſh and vaine error, the boldnes of prophane noueltie was to be repreſſed with authoritie of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Antiquitie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                     <p>NEITHER is this any new thing, but alway vſuall in the Church of God, that the more religious a man hath bene the more ready hath he all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes reſiſted nouell inuentions, exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples wherof many might be brought, but for breuity ſake I will only make choyce of ſome one which ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the Apoſtolique ſea by which al men may ſee moſt plainly with what force alwayes, what zeale, what inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the bleſſed ſucceſſion, of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtles haue defended the integri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty of that religion which they once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued. Therfore in times paſt <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinus</hi> of venerable memory Biſhope of <hi>Carthage,</hi> the firſt of all mortall men maintained this aſſertion againſt the deuine ſcripture, againſt the of the vniuerſall Church againſt the minde of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19754:15"/> all the preiſtes of his time againſt the cuſtome and traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his forefathers that rebaptization was to be admitted and put in practiſe. Which preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his procured ſo great domage and hurte to the Church, that not only it gaue all heriticks a paterne of ſacrilege but alſo miniſtred occaſion of errour to ſome Catholickes. When therfore euery where al men exclaimed againſt the nouelty of the doctrine, and all prieſtes in all places, each one accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his zeale did repugne, then Pope <hi>Steue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </hi> of bleſſed memory, biſhop of the Apoſtolique ſea, reſiſted in deed with the reſt of his felow byſhopes but yet more then the reſt, thinking it as I ſuppoſe reaſon ſo much to excell all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in deuotion towardes the faith, as he was ſuperiour to them in authoritie of place. To conclude in his Epiſtle which then was ſent to Afrike, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed the ſame in theſe wordes. <hi>That nothing was to bee innouated, but that which came by tradition ought to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued.</hi> For that holy and prudent man knew well, that the nature of pietie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19754:16"/> could admitt nothing elſe but only to deliuer and teach our children that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and that faith which we recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and learned of our forefathers, and that we ought to folow religion whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it doth lead vs and not to lead re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion whither it pleaſe vs, and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more proper to Chriſtian mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie and grauitie, then not to leaue vnto poſteritie our owne inuentions, but to preſerue and keepe that which our Predeceſſors left vs. What therfore was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the end of that wholle buſines? What elſe but common and vſuall, to wecte antiquitie was retained, nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie abandoned. But perhaps that new inuention lacked patrons and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders? To which I ſay on the contrary, that it had ſuch pregnant wittes, ſuch eloquent tonges, ſuch number of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants, ſuch ſhew of truth, ſuch teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of ſcripture, but gloſed after a new and naughtie faſhion, that all that conſpiracie and ſchiſme ſhoulde haue ſemed vnto me inuincible, had not the very profeſſion of noueltie it ſelfe, ſo taken in hand, vnder that name defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19754:17"/> with that title reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen the very ground of ſo great a ſchiſme. To conclude what force had the Councell or decree of Africke? By Gods prouidence none, but all things there agreed vpon were aboliſhed, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anulled, abrogated, as dreames, as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, as ſuperfluous. And O ſtrange change of the worlde, the authours of that opinion are iudged and thought Catholickes, the folowers accounted &amp; reputed Heretickes, the maſters diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, the ſchollers condemned, the writers of thoſe bookes ſhall be chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the kingdome of Heauen, the maintainers of thoſe books ſhall burne in Hell. For who donbteth but holy S. <hi>Ciprian,</hi> that light of all Saintes, that lanterne of Biſhops, and ſpectacle of Martirs, with the reſt of his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhall raigne with Chriſt for-euer. And contrariwiſe who is ſo wicked to deny that the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> and ſuch other peſtilent Heretickes, which by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of that Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell vaunt that they do practiſe rebaptization, ſhall burne for euer with the Deuill &amp; his Angells.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19754:17"/> Which iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in mine opinion ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to haue come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, for their fraudulent dealing eſpecially which endeuoring vnder the cloake of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans name, coningly to frame an hereſie commonly laye holde of ſome darke ſayings of one auncient Father or other, which by reaſon of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuritie may ſeeme to make for theire opinion, to thend they may be thought that whatſoeuer I know not what they bring forth to the worlde, neither to haue bene the firſt that ſo taught nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alone of that opinion: whoſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked deuice in mine opinion is worthie of dubble hatred, both for that they feare not to ſow their poiſoned ſeed of hereſie amongeſt others, and alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they blemiſhe the memorie of ſome holy man, &amp; as it were with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane handes caſt his dead aſhes into the wind bringing infamouſly that to light, which rather with ſilence were to be buried, folowing therin the ſteps of their father <hi>Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> who not only neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to couer the nakednes of vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Noë,</hi> but alſo ſhewed it to others
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19754:18"/> to laugh at, by which fact of his he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred ſo great a crime of impietie that <note place="margin">Gen. 9</note> his poſteritie was ſubiect to the male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of his ſinne: his bleſſed brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doing farr otherwiſe, who neither with their owne eies would violate the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of their reuerend father, nor yet permit it to remaine vncouered for other to behold, but going backward as the holy text ſaith they couerd him: which is as much to ſay that they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther approued with harte, nor blaſed with tong the holy mans fault, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore they &amp; their poſterity were rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with their fathers bleſſing. But to returne to our purpoſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
                     <p>VVE haue therfore much to feare the ſacrilege of a chan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged faith of a violated religion: from which fault not only the diſcipline of the eccleſiaſticall decree doth reſtraine vs, but the authoritie alſo of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles cenſure deterreth. For all men know how grauely, how ſeuerely, how
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19754:18"/> ſeriouſly the bleſſed Apoſtle S. PAVL inueigheth againſt certaine which with <note place="margin">Gal. 8</note> great leuitie <hi>Were ſo ſoone tranſferred from him that called them into the grace of Chriſt vnto another Goſpell, which is not an other: That had heaped vp to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </hi> 
                        <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4</note> 
                        <hi>ſelues maſters according to their owne de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſires, auerting their eares from truth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conuerted to fables: Hauing damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion becauſe they haue made voide their</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.</note> 
                        <hi>firſt faith.</hi> Whom thoſe men had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued of whom the ſame Apoſtle, in his epiſtle to the Romanes thus writeth <hi>I beſeech you brethren to marke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that make diſſentions and ſcandalls contrarie</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Ram. 16.</note> 
                        <hi>to the doctrine which you haue learned and auoide them, for ſuch doe not ſerue Chriſt our Lorde but theire owne bellie: And by ſweet ſpeaches and benedictions ſeduce the hartes of Innocents. That en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into houſes and lead captiue ſeelie wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3</note> 
                        <hi>loaden with ſinnes, which are lead away with diuers deſires, alwaies lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and neuer attaining to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of trewth. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aine ſpeakers and ſeducers who ſubuert wholle houſes tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Tit. 1</note> 
                        <hi>the thinges they ought not for fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19754:19"/> lucre: Men corrupt in their minde, reprobates concerning the faith: Proud,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3</note> 
                        <hi>and knowing nothing but languiſhing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout queſtions and ſtrife of wordes, that are depriued of the truth, that eſteeme a</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6. 1. Tim. 5.</note> 
                        <hi>gaine to be pietie: And with all idle they learne to go from houſe to houſe not only idle but alſo full of wordes and curious, ſpeaking thinges which they ought not:</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.</note> 
                        <hi>Which repelling a good conſcience haue made ſhipwracke about the faith: Whoſe prophane ſpeaches do much grow to impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie, and their ſpeach ſpreadeth as a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre.</hi> But that is alſo worth the noting which is written of them. <hi>But they ſhall</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 2. Tim. 3.</note> 
                        <hi>proſper no further for their follie ſhall be manifeſt to all as theirs alſo was.</hi> When therfore ſuch kind of men wandering vp and downe through Prouinces and cities to ſet their errors to ſale, came al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vnto the <hi>Galathians,</hi> who after they had heard the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and were delighted with the filthie druges of heretiall Nouelty caſting vp againe the heauenly Manna of the Apoſtolicke and Catholicke do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. The Apoſtle vſed his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie decreeing very ſeuerely in this ſort.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19754:19"/> 
                        <hi>But although we</hi> (quoth he) <hi>or an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel from heauen euangelize vnto you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Gal. 1. Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize ſignifieth ſuch preaching of good ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerneth the goſpell Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be he</note> 
                        <hi>that which we haue enangelized be he Anathema.</hi> What meaneth this that he ſayeth <hi>But although we,</hi> why did he not rather ſay <hi>But although I:</hi> That is to ſay, although <hi>Peter,</hi> although <hi>Andrew,</hi> although <hi>Iohn,</hi> yea finally al though the wholle companie of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles euangelize vnto you otherwiſe then we haue enangelized, be he accur ſed. A terrible cenſure, for maintaining the poſſeſſion of the firſt faith, not to haue ſpared him ſelfe, nor any other of the Apoſtles. But this is a ſmall matter: <hi>Although an Angell from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </hi> (quoth he) <hi>Euangelize vnto you, beſide that which I haue Euangelized be he Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema</hi> he was not contented for kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the faith once planted to make mention of mans weake nature vnleſſe alſo he included thoſe excellent crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Angells. <hi>Although</hi> we (qhoth he) <hi>or an Angell from heauen</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the holy Angells of Heauen can now ſinne, but this is the meaning of that he ſaith: Although (quoth he) that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19754:20"/> might be, which cannot be, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he be that goeth about to change the faith which was once planted, be he accurſed. But peraduenture he vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered thoſe words ſlightly and caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forth rather of humane affection then decreed them by any reaſon grounded in Gods word. God forbid: For it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, and that very earneſtly vrged, very often repeated. <hi>As I haue foretold you</hi> (quoth he) <hi>&amp; now againe I tell you If any body euangelize vnto you beſide that which you haue receaued be he Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</hi> He ſaid not if any man preach vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you beſide that which you haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued let him be bleſſed, let him be commended, let him be receaued, but <hi>Anathema,</hi> that is, ſeparated, thruſt out, excommunicated, leaſt the cruell infection of one ſheepe with his poiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned company corrupt the ſound flocke of Chriſt. But peraduenture this was giuen in commaundement only to the <hi>Galathians:</hi> then likewiſe were theſe precepts folowing commaunded only to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> to weete. <hi>If vve liue</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> 
                        <hi>in the ſpirite, in the ſpirite alſo lett vs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19754:20"/> vvalke, lett vs not be made deſirouſe of vaine glorie, prouoking one an other, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uying one an other</hi> and ſuch like which if it be abſurd to ſay, &amp; no man doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but that they were indifferently commaunded to all then certaine it is, that as theſe precepts touching maners include all, ſo likewiſe thoſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning faith and doctrine, exclude none And therfore as it is not lawfull for any to prouoke one another, to enuie one another, euen ſo it is vnlawfull for any to admitt or to receaue any other faith or religion then that which the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church euery where teacheth, or haply ſhal we be ſo mad to ſay that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was commaunded to curſe and ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematize him that preached any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then before had beene prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, &amp; that now it is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, then was that likewiſe which is there ſaide. <hi>But I ſay walke in the ſpirite and you ſhall not fulfill the deſires of the fleſh,</hi> then only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded but now is not; which if it be impious and dangerous ſo to beleeue, then of neceſſitie it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth that as theſe precepts of life &amp;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19754:21"/> manners are to be kept of all ages, ſo likewiſe thoſe ſet downe againſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uating of religion &amp; changing of faith, are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to all poſteritie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to preach vnto Chriſtian Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke men, beſids that which they haue receaued neuer was lawfull, no where is lawfull, at no time ſhall be lawfull.</p>
                     <p>And on the contrarie to ſay <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> and curſe thoſe which teach other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then once hath bene receaued, was at all times needful, is euery where conuenient, &amp; euer ſhall be requiſite. Which being ſo, is there any man ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo bold that dare teach that, which in the Church hath not bene taught, or of ſuch leuitie that will receaue ought beſides that which he hath receiued of the Church. Let that veſſell of electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that maiſter of the Gentiles, that trumpe of the Apoſtles, that preacher of the world, he that was acquainted with heauenly affaires, crie out, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine crie out in his epiſtles, to all men to all times, to all places, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer preacheth a new doctrine is to be accurſed. And on the contrarie parte,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19754:21"/> let certaine frogges corruptible gnates and flies, ſuch as the <hi>Pelagians</hi> be, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime and that to Catholickes. Wee being your authors (quoth they) we be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing your leaders, we being your inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, condemne that which before you did hold, hold that which before you condemned. Caſt away your olde faith, your forefathers lawes, your el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders conſtitutions, and receaue, what a gods name? I ſhake to ſpeake, for they are ſo proud and preſumptuous, that as they can not be maintained with-out ſin, ſo neither impngned without ſome blotte of offence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>VT ſome man will ſay, why then doth god very often permit certaine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and excellent men in the Church to preach vnto Catholicks a new religion. A very good queſtion and ſuch as deſerueth a more diligent and ample diſcourſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding I. will anſwer
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19754:22"/> out of mine owne head, but with the authoritie of ſacred ſcripture, and the doctrine of a notable maſter in Gods Church: let vs then heare holy <hi>Moiſes,</hi> let him giue vs the reaſon, why learned men and ſuch as for their great gift of knowledge are called of the Apoſtle Prophets, be ſome times permitted to preach new doctrine, which the olde teſtament allegorically calleth ſtrange gods, becauſe there opinions are ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerued &amp; honored of heretickes, as the gods were of the gentels: thus the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth bleſſed <hi>Moyſes</hi> in Deuteronomie. <hi>If there ſhall ariſe</hi> (quoth he) <hi>in the mid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Deut. 13</note> 
                        <hi>of thee a prophet or one which ſayth he hath ſeene a dreame,</hi> that is ſome ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the Church whoſe diſciples or followers ſuppoſe to teach by ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation from god: what then? <hi>&amp; ſhall fortell</hi> (quoth he) <hi>ſome ſigne or miracle, &amp; that ſhall happen which he hath ſayed:</hi> ſome greate maſter is here ſurely ment, and one of ſo deepe knowledge whom his folowers imagin not only to know things humane, but alſo to foreſee fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; ſuch as ſhall happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is far
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19754:22"/> aboue mans reach as the ſcholers for the moſt part of <hi>Valentinus, Donatus, Photi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus, Apollinaris,</hi> &amp; ſuch like did bragge that their maſters were. What folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth? <hi>And ſhall</hi> (quoth he) <hi>ſay vnto thee let vs go and folow ſtrange Gods, which thou knoweſt not, and let vs ſerue them.</hi> What is ment by <hi>ſtrange Gods,</hi> but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine errors, <hi>which thou knoweſt not,</hi> that is new and neuer heard of before, <hi>and let vs ſerue them,</hi> that is beleeue them, folow them. What the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? <hi>Thou ſhalt not</hi> (quoth he) <hi>heare the wordes of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet or Dreamer.</hi> And why I pray you? is not that forbidden by GOD to bee taught, which is by God forbidden to be heard? <hi>Becauſe</hi> (quoth he) <hi>the Lord your God doth tempt you, that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare whether you loue him or no, in your wholle heart, and in your wholle ſoule.</hi> The reaſon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is more cleare then day, why the prouidence of God doth ſome time ſuffer certaine teachers and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Church to preach certaine new opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that <hi>your Lord God</hi> (quoth he) <hi>may tempt you.</hi> And ſurely a great tentation it is, when as he whom you
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19754:23"/> thinke a Prophet, a diſciple of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, whom you eſteeme a Doctor and maintainer of the truth, whom you haue highly reuerenced, and moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tierly loued, when he ſodenly &amp; priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bringeth in pernicious errors which neither you can quickly ſpie, lead a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with preiudice of your old teacher nor eaſelie condemne, hindered with loue to your old maſter.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
                     <p>HERE ſome man haply doth ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire to ſee that proued by ſome eccleſiaſticall examples which by the authoritie of <hi>Moiſes</hi> hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy bene auouched. The demaund is reaſonable, and therfore of reaſon not long to be differred. Wherfore to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne with thoſe which are yet freſh in memorie, &amp; to the world beſt knowne. What kinde of tentation thincke you was that of late daies when that vngra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tious and curſed <hi>Neſtorius</hi> ſodenly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſheepe transformed into a wolfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to deuour the flocke of Chriſt, at
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19754:23"/> ſuch time as thoſe which were ſpoiled commonly tooke him for a ſheepe and therfore were more ſubiect to his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie. For who would haue eaſely ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined him to haue erred, whom euery man knew to haue bene choſen with ſuch iudgement of the Empire, who was ſo highly in grace with the Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, ſo much beloued of all holy men, ſo greatly in fauour with the people, who openly expounded the ſcriptures, and alſo confuted the peſtiferous er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the Iewes: why could not this man, by ſuch meanes eaſelie perſwade any, that he taught aright, preched a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, beleeued aright, who to ſmooth the way &amp; make entrance for his owne hereſie perſecuted &amp; preached againſt the blaſphemies of all others. But this was that which <hi>Moiſes</hi> ſaith: <hi>The Lord your God doth tempt you, if you loue him or no.</hi> And to paſſeouer <hi>Neſtorius</hi> in whom was alwaies more admiration, then profite, more fame the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> experience whom for ſome time humane fauour had made greater, then Gods grace ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted. Lett vs rather ſpeake of them
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19754:24"/> which endowed with many giftes, and men of greate induſtrie, haue bene no ſmall tentation to Catholickes, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Pauonians,</hi> in our Fathers memorie <hi>Photinus</hi> is recorded to haue tempted the Church of <hi>Sirminum,</hi> in which being preferred with the liking of all men vnto the dignitie of Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, for ſometime he behaued him ſelfe very Catholikely but ſodenly like that naughtie Prophet or Dreamer of whom <hi>Moiſes</hi> ſpeaketh he beganne to perſwade the people of God commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his charge, to folow other gods, that is ſtrange and vnknowen errors which before they were not acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with. But as this is vſuall, ſo that was verie pernitiouſe, that he had ſo great helpes and furtherance for the aduancing of ſo great wickednes: For he was both of an excelent witte, and ſingulerly well learned, and paſſing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent, as he which both in diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and writing was copious &amp; graue in either language as appeareth by the bookes which he wrote partly in greek and partly in the latin tong. But in hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19754:24"/> well that Chriſtes ſheepe commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his charge very vigila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in keeping the Catholike faith did ſpeedely remember <hi>Moiſes</hi> warning, and therfore albeit they admired much the eloquence of their Prophet and Paſtor: yet were they not ignorant of the temptation. And therefore whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they folowed as the cheefe leader of the flocke, the ſame very man after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they auoided as a rauening wolfe Neither do we learne only by <hi>Photinus</hi> but alſo by the example of <hi>Apollinaris</hi> the daunger of this eccleſiaſticall ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and therby alſo be admoniſhed diligently to keepe &amp; retaine our faith and religion. For this <hi>Apollinaris</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured his auditors great trouble &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of mind, whileſt the authoritie of the Church drew them one way, and the acquaintance of their maſter haled them another, ſo that wauering &amp; tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering betwixt both, they were vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine whether parte was beſt to be fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. But haply he was ſuch a one as eaſely deſerued to be contemned. Nay he was ſo famous and worthie a man,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19754:25"/> that in very may thinges he wone cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite too faſt. For who ſurpaſſed him in ſharpnes of witt? in exerciſe, in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? how many hereſies in many and greate bookes hath he ouerthrowne? how many errors againſt the faith hath he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futed? That moſt notable &amp; great worke of thirtie bookes in which with great waight of reaſon he confounded, the franticke cauills of <hi>Porphirius</hi> doth giue credit to my report, and teſtifie the truth of my relation. It were too long to rehearſe vp all his workes for which he might haue bene compared to the cheefe pillors of Gods Church, had not the prophane licentiouſneſſe of hereticall curioſitie, by inuenting I know not what new opinion ſpotted and diſcredited all his former labours, whereby his doctrine was accounted not ſo much an edification, as an eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall tentation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:19754:25"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
                     <p>HEREſome man perhaps requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to know what hereſies theſe men aboue named taught: that is, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storius, Appollinaris,</hi> &amp; <hi>Photinus.</hi> This pertaineth not to the matter, whereof we now intreat, for it is not out purpoſe to diſpute againſt each mans particuler error, but only by a few exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and clerely to proue, that to be moſt true which <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſaith, that if at any time any eccleſiaſticall maſter, yea &amp; a Prophet for interpreting the miſteries of the prophetical viſions, goeth about to bring in any new opinion into the Church, that the prouidence of god doth permitt it for our proofe &amp; triall. But becauſe it will be profitable, I will by a litle diſgreſſion breefely ſet downe what the forenamed heretickes <hi>Photi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Appollinaris,</hi> &amp; <hi>Nestorius</hi> taught This then is the hereſie of <hi>Photinus.</hi> he affirmeth that God is as the Iewes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue ſinguler and ſolitary, denyning the fulneſſe of the Trinitie not beleuing that there is any perſon of the word of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19754:26"/> God, or of the holy ghoſt he affirmeth alſo, that Chriſt was onlye man, who had his begining of the virgin MARY, teaching verie earneſtly that we ought to worſhipe only the perſon of god the father, &amp; to honor Chriſt only for man. This then was <hi>Photinus</hi> opinion. now <hi>Appollinaris</hi> vaunteth much as though he beleeued the vnitie of Trinitie with full &amp; ſound faith but yet blaſphemeth he manifeſtly againſt our Lordes incar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation. For he ſaith that our Sauiour either had not mans ſoule at all, or at leaſt ſuch a one, as was neither indued with mind or reaſon furthermore he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth that Chriſts body was not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fleſh of the holy virgin MARY, but deſcended from heauen into the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be of the Virgin, holding yet dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and inconſtantly ſome time that it was coeternall to the word of God, ſome time that it was made of the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the word: for he would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit two maner of ſubſtances in Chriſt, the one diuine, the other humane, the one of his Father, the other of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but did thinke that the verie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19754:26"/> of the word was deuided into two partes, as though the one remained in God, and the other was turned into fleſh, that whereas the truth ſaith, that Chriſt is one conſiſting of two ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, he contrary to the truth affirmeth, of the one diuinitie of Chriſt to be two ſubſtances: and theſe be the aſſertions of <hi>Apollinaris.</hi> But <hi>Neſtorius</hi> ſicke of a contrarie diſeaſe whileſt he faineth a diſtinction of two ſubſtances in Chriſt, ſodenly bringeth in two perſons: and with monſtrous wickednes, will needs haue two ſonnes of God, two Chriſtes, one that was God, and another that was man, one begotten of the Father, another begotten of his Mother. And therfore he ſaieth that the holy Virgin MARY is not to be called the mother of God, but the mother of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, that Chriſt which was borne of her was not God but man. And if any man thinke that in his bookes he ſaith there was one Chriſt and that he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched one perſon of Chriſt, I muſt needs confeſſe that he lacketh not ground to ſay ſo, for that he did either of craftie
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19754:27"/> pollicie, the rather to deceaue, that by ſome good thinges, he might the more eaſely perſwade nought as the Apoſtle ſaith. <hi>By the good thing he hath wrought</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 7</note> 
                        <hi>me death.</hi> Wherfore either craftely as I ſaid in certaine places of his writings he vaunteth to beleeue one perſon in Chriſt, or elſe ſurely he did hold, that after our Ladies deliuerie, two perſons became in ſuch ſort ſort one Chriſt that yet in the time of our Ladies co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ception or deliuerie, &amp; for ſome time after, there were two Chriſtes, and that Chriſt was borne firſt like vnto another man, and only was man, and not yet ioined in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie with the perſon of God the word, and that afterwarde the perſon of the word deſcended downe aſſuming and ioininge him ſelfe to that man in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of perſon, &amp; although he now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in glorie aſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted for ſome time yet there ſeemeth to haue bene no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixte him and other men. Thus then <hi>Neſtorius, Apollinaris, Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus,</hi> like mad dogges barked againſt the Catholicke Church: <hi>Photinus</hi> not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſing the Trinity: <hi>Apollinaris</hi> main
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19754:27"/> taining the nature of the Word conuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tible, &amp; not confeſſing two ſubſtances in Chriſt, denying alſo either the whol ſoule of Chriſt, or at leaſt that it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with mind and reaſon, beleeuing for his pleaſure what he liked of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond perſon in Trinitie. <hi>Neſtorius</hi> by defending either alwaies or for ſome time two Chriſtes. But the Catholicke Church beleeuing aright both of God and of our Sauiour, neither blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth againſt the miſterie of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nor againſt the incarnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt for it worſhipeth one Diuinitie in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and reuerenceth the equalitie of the Trinitie in one and the ſame maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſing one Chriſt, not two, and the ſelfe ſame both God and man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing in him one perſon, yet acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledging two ſubſtances, but yet belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one perſon: two ſubſtances, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the word of God is not mutable that it can be turned into fleſh: one per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon leaſt profeſſing two ſonnes, it may ſeeme to worſhip a quaternitie &amp; not to adore the Trinitie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:19754:28"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
                     <p>BVT it is worth the labor to declare this matter more plainely, more ſubſtantially, more diſtintly. In God is one ſubſtance and three perſons, in Chriſt be two ſubſtances, but one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone. In the Trinitie there is an other, and an other, but not another and an other thing. In our Sauiour is not an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; another, but an other &amp; other thing. How is there in the Trinitie an other and an other, but not another &amp; an other thing, Marry becauſe there is an other perſon of the father, an other of the ſonne, and an other of the holy ghoſt: But yet not an other &amp; another nature, but one &amp; the ſelfe ſame: How is there in our Sauiour another and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other thinge not another and another, becauſe there is another ſubſtance of the diuinitie and another ſubſtance of the humanitie, but yet the deitie &amp; the humanitie is not another and another but one and the ſelfe ſame Chriſt, one and the ſelfe ſame ſonne of God, and one and the ſelfe ſame perſon, of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19754:28"/> ſelfe ſame Chriſt and ſonne of God. As in a man the body is one thing, and the ſoule is another thing, but yet the body and the ſoule are but one and the ſelfe ſame man. In <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>Paule</hi> the ſoule is one thing, the body is another thing, &amp; yet the body &amp; the ſoule are not two <hi>Peters,</hi> nor the ſoule is not one <hi>Paul,</hi> and the body an other <hi>Paul,</hi> but one &amp; the ſelfe ſame <hi>Peter,</hi> one and the ſelfe ſame <hi>Paul,</hi> ſubſiſting of a doble and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe nature of the body and the ſoule. So therfore in one and the ſelfe ſame Chriſt there are two ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, but one a diuine ſubſtance, the other humane, the one of God the Father, the other of the Virgin his Mother, the one coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and equall to the Father, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubſtantiall to his Mother, yet one and the ſame Chriſt in both ſubſtances. Therefore there is not one Chriſt God another Chriſt man, not one increated, another created, not one impaſſible, another paſſible, not one equall to the Father, another leſſe then the Father, not one of the father, another of the mother, but one and the ſelfe ſame
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19754:29"/> Chriſt God and man, the ſame increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and created, the ſame incommuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and impaſſible, the ſame changed and ſuffered, the ſame equall and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to the father: The ſame begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of his father before all times, the ſame conceaued of his mother in time, perfect God and perfect man, in him as God is perfect Diuinitie, in him as man is perfect humanitie, perfect hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie I ſay becauſe it had both ſoule and body, yet a true body ſuch as our body is and ſuch as his mothers was, and a ſoule indued with vnderſtanding with mind and reaſon. There is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Chriſt, the Word, the Soule, the Fleſh, but yet all theſe togither is one Chriſt, one ſonne of God, our only Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour and Redeemer: One I ſay, not by any I knowe not what corruptible confuſion of the diuinitie &amp; humanitie togither, but by a certaine perfecte and ſinguler vnitie of perſon: for that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction did not chaunge or conuert either into other (which is the proper error of the <hi>Arians)</hi> but did rather ſo vnite both in one that as the ſingularity
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19754:29"/> of one and the ſame perſon remayneth alwayes in Chriſt ſo likewiſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties <note place="margin">Vide an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nota.</note> of both natures do for euer con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue, ſo that neither God euer begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to be a body, nor now at any time ceaſeth to be a bodie, which thinge is alſo more apparante by ſome humane example for not only in this world, but alſo in the next euery man ſhall conſiſt of body and ſoule, and yet neuer ſhall either the bodie be changed into the ſoule: or the ſoule euer conuerted into the bodie, but as euery man ſhall liue for euer, ſo for euer of neceſſitie in each man the differnce of either ſubſtance ſhall continue. So likewiſe in Chriſt each property of either ſubſtance, ſhall continue for euer, ſauing alwaies and reſeruing the vnity of perſon. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we often name this word <hi>Perſon</hi> and ſay that the ſonne of God was made man, we muſt take great heed that we ſeeme not to ſay that God the Word the ſecond perſon in Trinitie tooke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him our actions only in imitation and rather in ſhew and ſhadow &amp; not as a perfect &amp; very man practiſed hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19754:30"/> conuerſation: as we ſee vſed in Theaters and Stages where one man in a litle time, taketh vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him many parts of which notwithſtanding himſelfe is none, for as often as we counterfeite an other mans actions, we ſo exerciſe his office, that yet we be not thoſe men whoſe actions we take vpon vs for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a tragedie player (to vſe prophane examples and ſuch as the <hi>Maniches</hi> alledge) when he playeth the Preiſt or King, is therefore a Preiſt or King, for ſo ſoone as the tragedie endeth that perſon alſo which he played forth with ceaſeth: God keepe vs from this horrible &amp; wicked mockerie. Let this madnes be proper to the <hi>Maniches,</hi> which preaching a broade their owne fantaſies, affirme that God the ſonne of God not to haue bene ſubſtantiuelye the perſon of man, but to haue fained the ſame by ſuppoſed action and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. But the Catholicke faith af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth that the word of God was ſo made man, that he tooke vpon him our nature and the proprieties belonging to the ſame, not deceitfully &amp; in ſhew
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19754:30"/> but truely &amp; verily, and did ſuch things as belong to man, as his owne, and not as one that imitated other mens actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and was verily that which in life &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſation he did ſhewe him ſelfe to be, as we our ſelues alſo, in that we ſpeake vnderſtand, and ſubſiſt do not counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feite our ſelues to be men but are veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men. For neither <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> (to ſpeake of them eſpecially for example ſake) were men by imitation, but by ſubſiſtence, neither likewiſe did <hi>Paule</hi> counterfeite the Apoſtle or faine him ſelfe <hi>Paule,</hi> but was in veritie an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle and was <hi>Paule</hi> by ſubſiſtence. In like maner God the Word by aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and hauing fleſh; in ſpeaking do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſuffering, in fleſh, yet without any corruption of his nature vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed perfectly to performe this, to weet not that he ſhould imitate or counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feite, but exhibite him ſelfe a perfecte man, not that he ſhould ſeeme or be thought a very man, but ſhould in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ſo be and ſubſiſt. Therfore as the ſoule ioined to the fleſh and yet not tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned into the fleſh, doth not imitate a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19754:31"/> man but is a man, &amp; not a man in ſhew and apparance but in ſubſtance. So God the Word without any conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of him felfe, vniting him ſelfe to man was made man not by confuſion, not by mutation, but by ſubſiſting. Lett that expoſition therfore of a fained and counterfeite perſon vtterly be reiected in which alwaies one thing is in ſhew, and an other in deed, in which he that doth ought is neuer the ſame perſon whom he repreſenteth: for God forbid that we ſhould beleeue that God the Word tooke vpon him the perſon of man after ſuch a deceitfull manner, but rather in this ſort that his ſubſtance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mutable in itſelfe, &amp; yet taking vpon him the nature of perfecte man, was him ſelfe fleſh, was him ſelfe a man, was him ſelfe the perſon of a man not deceitfully but truely, not in i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation, but in truth &amp; ſubſtance, not finally after that ſort which with actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold deſiſt, but after that maner which perfectlye in ſubſtance ſhould perſiſt. This vnitie therfore of perſon in Chriſt was not framed, and finiſhed after the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19754:31"/> virgins deliuerie, but in her very wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be. For we muſt diligently take heed that we confeſſe Chriſt not onely one, but alſo to haue bene alwaies one, becauſe it is an intollerable blaſphemy to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t him now to be one and yet contende that once he was not one, but two, that is one after the time of his Baptiſme, but two in the time of his Natiuitie, which great ſacriledge we can not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe auoid, but by confeſſing that man was vnited to God in vnitie of per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, not in his aſcention, not in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, not in his baptiſme, but in his mothers wombe and immaculate conception: by reaſon of which vnitie of perſon both the proprieties of God are indifferently and promiſcually at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to man, and the proprieties of man aſcribed to God: Hereof it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that which is written in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that the ſonne of man deſcended from Heauen, and the Lord of maieſty was Crucified vpon earth: Hereof alſo <note place="margin">Ioan. 6</note> it proceedeth that we ſay that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Lordes fleſh was made, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Lords body was framed that the very word
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19754:32"/> of God was made, the very wiſdome of God was repleniſhed with created knowledge as in the foreſight of God <hi>His hands &amp; feet are ſaid to be digged:</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Pſa. 21.</note> Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this vnitie of perſon, I ſay it proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth by reaſon of like miſtery that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fleſh of the word of God was borne of his pure &amp; immaculate morher, we do moſt Catholickly beleeue that God him ſelfe the Word was borne of the Virgin and moſt impiouſly the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is maintained: Which being ſo god forbid that any one ſhould go about to depriue the holy Virgin MARY of her priuiledges of gods fauour as her eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall glorie: For ſhe is by the ſinguler grace of our Lord and God her ſonne to be confeſſed moſt truely and moſt bleſſed to haue bene the mother of God, but yet not in ſuch ſorte as an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious hereticke imagine and ſuſpecte, who affirme that ſhe is to be reputed in name only and appellation the mother of God, as ſhe forſoth which brought forth that man which afterwarde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came God, as we ſay ſuch a woman is the mother of a Prieſt or Biſhoppe not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19754:32"/> becauſe ſhe brought him that then was either Prieſt or Biſhop, but by genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that man which afterwarde was made a Prieſt or Biſhoppe: not in that manner I ſay the bleſſed Virgin is to be called the mother of God, but rather becauſe as haue bene ſaide, that moſt holy miſterie was finiſhed in her ſacred wombe which by reaſon of a ſinguler and one onely vnitie of perſon as the Word in fleſh is fleſh, ſo man in God is God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
                     <p>BVT now what hath already bene ſaid towching the foreſaid hereſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es or concerning the Catholicke faith, let vs in few wordes and compe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diouſly for memorie ſake repeate them ouer againe, that therby with more facilitie they may be vnderſtoode &amp; with more ſuretie retained. Accurſed therfore be <hi>Photinus</hi> not admitting the fulnes of the Trinitie and affirming our Sauiour Chriſt to haue bene only man. Accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be <hi>Appollinaris</hi> maintaining in Chriſt corruption of changed diuinitie
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19754:33"/> and bereauing him of the proprietie of perfect humanity. Accurſed be <hi>Neſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> denying God to haue bene borne of a virgin, teaching two Chriſtes and ſo abandoninge the faith of the Trinitie bringing in a quaternitie. But bleſſed be the Caholicke Church which ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth one God in perfecte Trinitie and likewiſe worſhippeth equalitie of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie in one diuinity, ſo that neither ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularitie of ſubſtance co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>foundeth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie of perſons nor diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie ſeperateth vnitie of deitie. Bleſſed I ſay be the Church which beleeueth in Chriſt two true and perfect ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces but one only perſon, ſo that neither diſtinction of natures doth deuide the vnitie of perſon, nor vnitie of perſon doth confound the difference of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. Bleſſed I ſay be the Church which to thend ſhe may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe Chriſt alwaies to be and to haue bene one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth man vnited to God, not after our Ladies deliuery but euen then in his mothers wombe. Bleſſed I ſay bee the Church which vnderſtandeth God made man not by any conuerſion
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19754:33"/> of nature but by reaſon and meanes of perſon, and not that a fained and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie perſon but ſubſtantially ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; permanent. Bleſſed I ſay be the Church which teach that this vnitie of perſon hath ſo great force that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon therof by a miſterie ſtrange and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable ſhe aſcribeth vnto man the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prieties of God, &amp; attributeth to God the proprieties of man. For by reaſon of this vnitie of perſon ſhe confeſſeth that man as he was God deſcended from Heauen, and God as he was man was made vpon earth, ſuffered &amp; was Crucified. Bleſſed therfore is that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable, happie and ſacred confeſſion and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable to thoſe ſupernall prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Angells, which glorifieth one Lorde God with triple ſanctification. For this is the principal reaſon why the Church teacheth the vnitie of Chriſt, leaſt otherwiſe ſhe ſhould exceed the miſterie of the Trinitie.</p>
                     <p>And let this ſuffice touchinge this matter ſpoaken by way of digreſſion: hereafter if it pleaſe God I will intreate and declare theſe pointes more copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19754:34"/> Now to returne to our former purpoſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. X.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>e haue ſaid in the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that in the Church of God the error of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is a great tentation to the people, and the more learned he were that erred, ſo much the greater was the tentation: Which we ſhewed firſt by the authority of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture, afterward by the examples eccleſiaſticall of thoſe men, which for ſome time reputed &amp; accounted ſound in faith, yet at laſt fell either in ſome other mans error, or elſe coined a new hereſie of their owne: This ſurely is a greate matter, profitable to be learned and neceſſarie to be reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred, which once again we muſt inculcate &amp; make plaine by greater ſtore of exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, that almoſt all Catholickes may know that with the Church they ought to receiue Doctors and not with the Doctors to forſake the faith of the Church. But I am of this opinion, that although I
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19754:34"/> could bring forth many to ſhewe this kinde of tentation, yet there is almoſt none which can be compared to the tentation of <hi>Origen,</hi> in whom were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie many giftes, ſo rare, ſo ſinguler, ſo ſtrange, that in the begining any wold haue thought that his opinions might haue bene beleued of all men. For if life procureth authoritie, he was a man of great induſtrie, of great chaſtititie, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience &amp; labour, if familie or learning who more noble? being of that houſe, which was honorable for martyrdome, him ſelfe afterward for Chriſt depriued not of father only but alſo ſpoiled of all his patrimonie, &amp; ſo much he profited in the miſteries of holy pouertie, that as it is reported, for the confeſſion of Chriſtes name he often indured much affliction. Neither was he only ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with theſe giftes, all which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſerued for tentation, but was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued alſo with force of witte, ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, ſo quicke, ſo delicate, that he far excelled almoſt all other whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. A man of ſuch wonderfull lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; erudition that there were few
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19754:35"/> things in Diuinitie, in humane Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phie haplye nothing which he had not perfectly attained: who hauing gotten the treaſures of the greeke tongue, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured alſo about the hebrew. And for his eloquence what ſhould I ſpeake of? whoſe talke was ſo pleaſant, ſo dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable, ſo ſweet, that in mine opinion, not wordes but honie flowed from his mouth. What thinges were ſo hard to beleeue which with force of argument he made not plaine, what ſo difficulte to bring to paſſe, which he made not to ſeeme eaſie? But perchance he main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tained his aſſertions by arguments on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: Nay without queſtion there was ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer any Doctor which vſed more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of ſacred ſcripture. But yet hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pelie he wrote not much? No man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing more, yea ſo much that in mine opinion all his workes are ſo far from being read ouer, that they can not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiblie all be found, who not to lacke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie furtherance to learning, liued alſo vntill he was paſſing olde. But yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce vnfortunate in his ſchollers: What man euer more happie, hauing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19754:35"/> trained vp and bene maſter to infinite Doctors, to Preiſtes without number, to Confeſſors and Martirs. Now who is able to proſecute with wordes, in what admiration he was with all men? in what glory, in what credite &amp; grace? Who more zealous in religion repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not to him, from the furtheſt partes of the world? What Chriſtian did not almoſt worſhip him as a Prophet? what Philoſopher did not honour him as a maſter, and how greatly he was reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced not only of priuate men, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the Empire it ſelfe, hiſtories doe ſpeake which reporte that he was ſent for of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Emperors mother to weet, for his merit of heauenly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with the grace and loue wherof he was inflamed. His epiſtles alſo te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the ſame thing which with autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie of a Chriſtian maſter he wrote vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Phillip</hi> the Emperor the firſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an amongeſt all the Romane Princes. And if any man vpon our report admit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth not the teſtimonie of a Chriſtian touching his wonderfull knowledge, and learning, at leaſt let him receaue
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19754:36"/> the confeſſion of an heathen Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher. For that impious <hi>Porphirie</hi> ſaith that him ſelfe being but yet as it were a boy, moued with his fame, trauailed vnto <hi>Alexandria</hi> where he did ſee him being then olde, but yet ſuch a one &amp; ſo learned as he that had attained to the perfection of all knowledge. Day would ſooner faile me, then I coulde touch though breiflye thoſe notable gifts which were in that man, all which notwithſtanding pertained not only to the glorie of religion, but alſo to the greatnes of the temptation. For who is he that would willingly haue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a man of ſuch wit, of ſo deepe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, of ſo rare grace, and would not ſooner haue vſed that ſaying, that he had rather erre with <hi>Origen</hi> then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue aright with others. And what ſhould I ſay more, the matter came to that iſſue, that as the end ſhewed, not an vſuall &amp; commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but a paſſing dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous tentation of ſo worthie a man, ſo famous a Doctor, ſo notable a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, caried very many from the true and ſound faith of the Church: For this
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19754:36"/> 
                        <hi>Origen</hi> ſo rare and ſinguler a man, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing the grace of God, to inſolently flattering him ſelfe, to much in his own witte, beleeuing him ſelfe more then reaſon would, litle eſteeming the olde ſimplicitie of Chriſtian religion, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming to be wiſer then all other, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the traditions of the Church, and the olde Fathers documents, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo far in expounding cartaine chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters of the ſcripture after a new faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vntill he deſerued, that the Church of God ſhould alſo ſay of him. <hi>Yf there ariſe vp in the middeſt of thee a Prophet,</hi> &amp; a litle after <hi>thou ſhalt not heare</hi> (quoth he) <hi>the wordes of that Prophet.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <hi>becauſe</hi> (quoth he) <hi>your Lorde God doth tempt you whether you loue him or no.</hi> And ſurely it is not only a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation but alſo a great tentation when a man carieth away ſecretly and by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and litle the Church depending vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him (admiring his witt, knowledge eloquence, conuerſation, &amp; grace, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſuſpecting him, nothing fearing him) ſodenly from the olde religion to a prophane &amp; new doctrine. But ſome
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19754:37"/> will ſay that <hi>Origens</hi> bookes be corrup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted: I will not gaine ſay it, but rather it were ſo: for that hath both bene ſaid &amp; written of ſome not only Catholickes, but alſo Hereticks. But this is now the point we haue to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, that althogh not he, yet the bookes paſſing abrode vnder his name are a greate tentation, which ſtuffed with many horrible blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, are read and vſed, loued, and liked, not as the bookes of others, but as his owne workes: ſo that although <hi>Origen</hi> gaue no cauſe of erroneous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, yet his authoritie hath bene the occaſion why the error hath bene liked and folowed.</p>
                     <p>The caſe alſo of <hi>Tertullian</hi> is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame with the former: for as <hi>Origen</hi> is to be thought the beſt amongeſt the Greeke Doctors, ſo <hi>Tertullian</hi> without controuerſie the cheefe of all the latin. For who was more learned then hee? Who in Diuinitie or Humanitie more practiſed? for by his great and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full capacitie of witt, he attained to, &amp; imbraced all Philoſophie, all the ſectes of Philoſophers, all their authors and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19754:37"/> patrons, all their learning, all ſortes of hiſtories and ſtudies. And for his witt, was he not ſo excellent, ſo graue, ſo ſharpe, that he almoſt vndertooke the ouerthrow of nothing which either by quicknes of witt or waight of reaſon he cruſhed not in peeces. Now who is able to ſet downe the commendacion and praiſe which his ſtile and phraſe of ſpeach deſerued, which was ſo fraught (I know not how) with that force of reaſon, that ſuch as could not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled: whoſe almoſt ſo many wordes, ſo many ſentences, ſo many ſences, ſo many victories. This is well knowne to <hi>Marcion</hi> and <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles,</hi> well knowne to <hi>Praxeas,</hi> and <hi>Hermogenes,</hi> the Iewes vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this, the Gentiles haue tried it, the <hi>Gnoſtikcs</hi> haue proued it. and diuers others haue felt it: whoſe blaſphemouſe opinions he hath ouerthrowne with his many &amp; great volumes, as it had bene with thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and lightning. And yet this man after all this, this <hi>Tertullian</hi> I ſay, not holding the Catholicke religion, that is the vniuerſall and olde faith, being
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19754:38"/> far more eloquent then fortunate, cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging afterwarde his minde, did at laſt that which the bleſſed Confeſſor <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larie</hi> in a certaine place writeth of him. <hi>He diſcredited</hi> (quoth he) <hi>with his lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter error his probable writings:</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was alſo a greate tentation in the Church. But hereof I will ſaye no more, only this I add, that by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending againſt the precept of <hi>Moiſes,</hi> for true prophecies the new madneſſe of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tanus</hi> ſpringing vp in the church and theſe mad dreames of a new do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the franticke woman, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued that we ſhould alſo ſay of him and his writinges. <hi>Yf a Prophete ſhall riſe vp in the mideſt of thee</hi> and ſtraight after, <hi>thou ſhalt not heare the wordes of that Prophet.</hi> Why ſo? <hi>Becauſe</hi> (qnoth he) <hi>your Lord God doth tempt you whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you loue him or no.</hi> We ought ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euidently to note by theſe ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſo great &amp; diuers, others ſuch waigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie examples, and by the law of Deute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronomie moſt cleerely to vnderſtand that if at any time any eccleſiaſticall teacher ſtraieth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the faith, that gods
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19754:38"/> prouidence doth ſuffer that for our tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, whether we loue him or no in our wholle hart and in our wholle ſoule.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
                     <p>VVHICH being ſo, he is a true and perfect ſincere Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke that loueth Gods truth, that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his body the Church, that prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth nothing beefore the religion of God, nothinge before the Catholicke faith, not any mans authority, not loue, not will, not eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, not philoſophie but contemning all theſe things, ſetled in faith; ſtable &amp; permane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whatſoeuer he knoweth the Catholicke Church vniuerſally in old time to haue holden, purpoſeth with him ſelfe only to hold and beleeue: and therfore whatſoeuer new doctrine and not before heard of ſuch a one perceaue to be brought in of ſome one man, beſide or contrarie to the olde Saintes and Doctors, lett him know that not to pertaine to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion but rather to tentation, for his proofe and triall, eſpecially being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19754:39"/> with the ſaving of the Apoſtle Sainte <hi>Paule.</hi> for this is that which he writeth in his firſt epiſtle to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians. There muſt</hi> (quoth he) <hi>be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies alſo that they which are approued may be made manifeſt amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt you.</hi> As thogh he ſhould ſay. This is the cauſe why the authors of hereſies are not ſtraight rooted out by God, that the prooued may bee made manifeſt, that is euery one may appeare how ſtedfaſtly, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and conſtantly, he loueth the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke faith. And certaine it is that ſtraight vpon the ſpringing vp of any Noueltie, the waightie corne is diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the light chaffe, then is that eaſelie ſhaken out of the floare which before lightly remained in the floare, for ſome by and by leape away, others only ſhaken are afraid to periſh, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to returne, remaining woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, halfe dead, half aliue, like vnto thoſe which haue druncke ſo much poi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, as neither killeth, nor digeſteth, neither bringeth death, nor yet permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to liue. Alas the miſerable ſtate of ſuch perſons, with what ſeas of cares,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19754:39"/> with what ſtormes are they toſſed? for ſome time as the winde driueth them, they are caried away headlong into er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, an other time coming again to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, they are ſhaken &amp; beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary waues ſtriuing togither, ſomtime with raſh preſumption they allow ſuch thinges, as ſeeme vncertaine, an other time of puſillanimitie they feare thoſe thinges which are certaine, doubtfull which way to take, which way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, what to deſire, what to auoide, what to holde, what to let go: which miſerie &amp; affliction of a wauering harte and not ſetled, were they wiſe, is the ſalue of Gods mercie towardes them. For this is the reaſon why (being out of the ſafe porte of the Catholike faith) they are ſhaken, toſſed, and almoſt kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ſtormes and troubles, to the end they ſhould ſtrike downe the ſailes of their proud mind, which they nough tely hoiſed vp to the windes of nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp; ſo retire &amp; keepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with in the moſt ſure port of their calme and good mother, &amp; firſt caſt vp thoſe bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; turbule<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t waters of errors that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19754:40"/> they may drinke of the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing riuers of liuelie &amp; runing water. Let them learne to forget well, which well they haue not learned, and thoſe arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles which the Church teacheth, and by reaſon are to be attained to: let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Gods name comprehend, and thoſe which ſurpaſſe reaſon let them by faith beleeue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
                     <p>VVHICH being ſo, ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times calling to minde and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring the ſelfe ſame thing: I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſufficiently maruell at the great madnes of ſome men, at ſo great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie of a blinded harte, to conclude at ſo greate a licentious deſire to error, that they be not content with the rule of faith once deliuered vs, and receiued from our aunceſtors, but do euery day ſearch and ſeeke for new doctrine, euer deſirous to add, to change, and to take a way ſom thing from religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as though that were not the doctrine of God, which was once ſufficiently reuealed, but rather mans inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19754:40"/> but by continuall correction (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther corruption) come to perfection: Whereas the diuine ſcriptures crye out <hi>Do not tranſlate the boundes which thy fathers haue ſet downe,</hi> and <hi>Do not iudge ouer thy iudge.</hi> And, <hi>the Serpent will bite him that cutteth the hedge.</hi> And that ſaying of the appoſtles by which all wicked nouelties of all heritickes haue often bene cut in peces as it were with a ſpiritual! ſworde and alwaies hereafter are. <hi>O Timothie keepe the depoſitum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiding the prophane nouelties of voices and oppoſitions of falſly called knowledge which certaine promiſinge haue erred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the faith.</hi> And yet for all this, ſome there be ſo ſhameles, ſo impudent, ſo obſtinate, which will not yelde to ſuch force of diuine ſcripture, which be not moued with ſuch waight of reaſon nor yet ſhaken with ſuch heauenly ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mers, to conclude which be not beaten in peeces with ſuch celeſtiall lightning: <hi>Auoide</hi> (quoth he) <hi>the prophane nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of voices.</hi> He ſaieth not auoide an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities, he ſaieth not auoid auncient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, nay rather ſheweth what contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19754:41"/> ſhould folow. For if nouelty is to be auoided, antiquitie is to be retained if nouelty be prophane, antiquitie is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, <hi>&amp; oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> (quoth he) <hi>of falſly cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led knowledge.</hi> Verily the name of know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge in the ſchooles of Hereticks is falſe, where ignorance is called know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, miſt, reputed cleerenes, &amp; dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes termed by the name of light. <hi>Which certaine</hi> (quoth he) <hi>promiſing haue er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red about the faith.</hi> What promiſed they, when they erred about the faith? What elſe, but I know not what new and vnknowen doctrine? For you may heare ſome of them ſay. O ye vnwiſe and ſeelie ſoules which commonly are called Catholickes, come and learne the true faith, which no creature vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth beſides vs, which hath bene hidden, many hundred of yeeres paſt, but of late hath bene reuealed and laid open, but learne it priuily, learne it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, for it will delight you. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine when you haue learned it, teach it ſecretly, that the world may not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, that the Church may not know it, for it is graunted to fewe to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19754:41"/> vnderſtand the ſecret of ſo great a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie. Are not theſe thincke you the wordes of that harlot which in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerbes of <hi>Salomon</hi> calleth vnto her the paſſengers: <hi>Who is</hi> (quoth ſhe) <hi>moſt</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prou.</hi> 9</note> 
                        <hi>foole amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt you let him turne vnto me.</hi> And ſuch as be of ſmall iudgement ſhe exhorteth, ſaying. <hi>Touch willingly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete bread, and drinke ſweet water pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uily.</hi> What foloweth? <hi>But he knoweth not</hi> (quoth he) <hi>how in her company earth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly men do periſh.</hi> who be theſe earthly men? Let the Apoſtle declare: <hi>Thoſe</hi> (quoth he) <hi>which haue erred about the faith.</hi> But it is worth the labour more diligently to examine the Apoſtle his whole Chapter. <hi>O Timothie</hi> (quoth he) <hi>keepe the depoſitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auoiding prophane no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelties of voices.</hi> This exclamation O, both ſheweth foreſight and alſo argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth charitie: for he foreſawe certaine errors which before hand he was ſory for: who at this day hath the place of <hi>Timothie?</hi> but either the whole Church or eſpecially the wholle body of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, who ought them ſelues to haue the wholle knowledge of diuine reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19754:42"/> and alſo to inſtruct others, what is ment by <hi>keepe the depoſitum.</hi> Keepe it quoth hee for feare of theeues, for daunger of enemies, leaſt when men be a ſleepe they ouer-ſow cockell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the wheat, which the ſonne of man hath ſowed in his feild. <hi>Keepe</hi> (quoth he) <hi>the depoſitum.</hi> What is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by this <hi>depoſitum:</hi> that is, that which is <note place="margin">An exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of S. Paules wordes.</note> committed to thee, not that which is inuented of thee: that which thou haſt receaued, not that which thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed: a thing not of witt, but of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: not of priuate vſurpation, but of publicke tradition: a thing brought to thee: not brought forth of thee: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou muſt not be an author, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper: not a beginner, but a folower: not a leader, but a comer after: <hi>Keepe the depoſitum.</hi> Preſerue the talent of the Catholicke faith pure and ſincere, that which is committed to thee, let that remaine with thee, and that deliuer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people. Thou haſt receiued gold render then gold, I will not haue one thing for another. Do not for gold giue me either impudently leade or craftily
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19754:42"/> braſſe, I will not the ſhew, but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie nature of golde it ſelfe. <hi>O Timothie, O Preiſte,</hi> O Teacher, O Doctour, if Gods gift hath made thee meete and ſufficient for thy witt, exerciſe and lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning, ſhew thy ſelfe <hi>Beſeelel,</hi> that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine workeman in building of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall tabernacle, ingraue thoſe preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones of Gods religion, faithfully ſet them, wiſely adorne them, put vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them brightnes, giue them grace, giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bewtie. That which men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beleeued obſourely, let them by thy expoſition vnderſtand more cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Let poſteritie reioice for comming to the knowledge of that by thy means, which antiquitie without that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge had in veneration. Yet for all this, in ſuch ſort deliuer what thou haſt learned, that albeit thou teacheſt new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and after a new maner: yet thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer preach a new religion and deliuer a new faith.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
                     <p>BVT peraduenture ſome will ſay, ſhall we then haue no increaſe of religion in the Church of Chriſt? no
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19754:43"/> growing on, no proceeding forward? To which I anſwere and ſay. Let vs a-Gods name haue the greateſt and moſt that may be. For who is either ſo enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to men, or hatefull to God which wold labour to ſtop or hinder that? but yet in ſuch ſort &amp; with this prouiſo that it may appeare to be truely an increaſe in faith &amp; not proue to be a change in religion for this is the nature of ſuch thinges as increaſe, that in them ſelues they become and grow greater. And this is the nature of a change &amp; muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ſome thing be turned from one thing which it was, to an other which it was not: Conuenient it is and very neceſſary, that the vnderſtanding, knowledge, and wiſdome, aſ well of e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uery man in particuler, as of all in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: as well of one a lone, as of the wholle Church in generall, of all ages in times paſt, ſhould aboundantly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and go forwarde, but yet for all that, onely in his owne kinde and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that is in the ſame faith, in the ſame ſence, in the ſame ſentence. In this caſe let the religion of our ſoule
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19754:43"/> imitate the nature of our bodies, which although with proces of time they paſſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouer many yeeres, yet they remaine the ſame that they were. There is great difference betwixt floriſhing youth &amp; withered age, yet the ſelfe ſame men become olde which before were yong ſo that although the ſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one and the ſelfe ſame man be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, yet one very nature and perſon, doth ſtill remaine. The limmes &amp; mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers of infants be ſmall, of young men great, yet not diuers but the very ſame. So many iointes as young childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſo many haue they when they be men, and if any partes there be, which with increaſe of yeeres ſpring forth, thoſe before by nature were in man virtually planted, ſo that no newe thing come forth in olde men, which before were not contained in them being yet chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Wherfore there can be no doubt, but that this is the due and right order of growing, the moſt naturall &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt way of increaſing only to haue in olde yeeres, thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, thoſe partes and iointes which the wiſdome of our
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19754:44"/> Creator before framed when we were yet but litle ones: And therfore if a man be afterward cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged into ſome other ſhape or likenes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his nature require: or if the number of his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers be more or leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nature preſcribeth: then of neceſſitie the wholle body muſt either periſhe or become monſtrouſe, or at leaſt remaine lame &amp; maimed. In like manner Chriſtian religion muſt folow theſe rules of increaſing and growing, to weet, that with yeeres it waxe more ſound, with time become more ample, with continuance be more exalted, yet remaine pure and incorrupt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue full and perfect with each of his partes, and as it were with all his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and proper ſences: And further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more that it admit no change or muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſuſtaine no loſſe of his proprietie, no varietie or mutabilitie in definition: for example ſake. Our forefathers in olde time in the ſpirituall feilde of the Church, ſowed the wheaten ſeede of true faith and religion, it were now ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry iniurious and vnreaſonable, that we their poſteritie in ſteed of perfecte and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19754:44"/> true wheate ſhould reape the falſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of cockle: And contrariwiſe it is reaſon and very conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and ending not diſagreeing with it ſelfe, we ſhould of the increaſe of wheate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeed reape the fruit of whea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten religion, ſo that when with tract of time, any of thoſe firſt ſeedes beginne to budd and come forth, let them be tilled &amp; trimmed, yet without cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging ought of the proprietie of the corne ſpringing vp: and albeit faſhion, ſhape and diſtinction, be added &amp; put to, yet muſt the nature of each kinde remaine and abide. For God forbid that thoſe roſie plantes of the Catholike doctrine ſhould be chaunged into thirſtles and thornes, God forbid I ſay, that in this ſpirituall paradiſe, of the ſlippes of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon &amp; Balſme ſhould ſodenly grow vp darnel and poiſon. Therfore what ſoeuer hath by the grace of God and our Fathers faith beene ſowen in this Church, reaſon it is that the ſame be cultiuated &amp; maintained by the indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: meet that it floriſh &amp; waxe ripe, conuenient it grow &amp; come
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19754:45"/> to perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for lawfull it is that thoſe auncient articles of heauenly philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, ſhoulde be trimmed, ſmoothed, and poliſhed: but vnlawfull it is that they ſhould be changed, mangled and maimed. And albeit they receaue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuitie, light, and diſtinction, yet of neceſſitie muſt they retaine their ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſoundnes, and proprietie. For if once this licentiouſnes of wicked fraud be admitted, I tremble to ſpeake what daunger is like to enſue of raſing and abandoning religion, for if we take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way any parte of the Catholicke faith, ſtraight waies other partes, and after that other, and againe other, and that as it were of cuſtome and by law ſhall be abandoned. And what followeth when euery parte by litle and litle is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed but that in concluſion the wholle corps of religion at one blow be refuſed and reiected. And contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe if new things and olde, forraine and domeſticall, prophane and ſacred, begin once to be confounded togither then muſt needs this cuſtome generally folow, that nothing hereafter remaine
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19754:45"/> in the Church vntowched, nothinge without corruption, nothing ſounde, nothing pure, nothing ſincere, and ſo where before was the ſacred ſchoole of chaſte and immaculate truth, there ſhall be a very brothel houſe of wicked &amp; filthie errors. But God of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes deliuer his ſeruants fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch minds, and let the impious rather &amp; graceleſſe follow that furious &amp; mad proceeding For the Church of Chriſt is a carefull &amp; diligent keeper of religion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to her charge, ſhe neuer cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth or alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in it any thing, ſhe diminiſheth nothing, nothing ſhe addeth: What is neceſſarie ſhe loſeth not, what is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous ſhe forceth not, her owne ſhe maintaineth, not her owne ſhee vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not, but with all induſtrie labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth only about this one thing, that is by faithfull &amp; prudent handling of our forefathers doinges, what by them in times paſt was well entered &amp; begone, ſhe poliſheth: what the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was well poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and declared ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmeth: what then was confirmed &amp; defined ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth. To conclude what hath ſhe els
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19754:46"/> endeuoured by the decrees of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells but that, that doctrine which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was ſimplie credited, the ſame af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward ſhould be more diligently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued: that religion which before was taughtmore ſlowly, the ſame afterward ſhold be preached more inſtantly: That faith which before was more ſecurely reuerenced, the ſame afterward ſhould more carefully be practiſed. This I ſay alwaies &amp; nothing els hath the Church prouoked with the nouelties of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes ſet downe by the decrees of her Councells, to weet onely to confirme that to poſteritie by writing (compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding a great ſumme of things in few wordes and often times for more eaſie vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to an olde article of faith geuing a new name) which before by tradition ſhe had receaued of her fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XIIII.</head>
                     <p>BVT to returne to the Apoſtle. <hi>O Timothie</hi> (quoth he) <hi>keepe tho de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum auoyding prophane nouelties of voices.</hi> Auoyde (quoth he) as a viper,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19754:46"/> as a ſcorpian, as a baſiliske, leaſt they infecte thee, not only by towching, but alſo with their very eies &amp; breath. what is ment by <hi>Auoide</hi> that is, not ſo much as to eate with any ſuch, what <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor</hi> 5</note> importeth this <hi>(Auoide) yf</hi> any man (quoth he) <hi>come vnto you and bring</hi> not <hi>this doctrine,</hi> what doctrine but the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke and vniuerſall, and that which with ſounde traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the truth, hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued one &amp; the ſelfe ſame, through all ſucceſſions of times, and that which ſhall continue to the worldes ende. What the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? <hi>Receaue him not</hi> (quoth he) <hi>into the houſe, nor ſay God ſaue you, for</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">2. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 7</note> 
                        <hi>he that ſaieth vnto him God ſaue you, communicateth with his wicked workes. Prophane nouelties of voices</hi> (quoth he) what is <hi>(Prophane).</hi> Thoſe which haue no holines in them, no iote of religion wholie vnknowne to the Church which is the temple of God. <hi>Prophane nouelties of voices</hi> quoth he <hi>(of voices)</hi> that is nouelties of opinions, nouelties of things, nouelties of ſenſes, contrarie to our forefathers faith, contrarye to antiquitie, which if we admitte and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19754:47"/> of neceſſitie the faith of our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed aunceſtors, either all, or a greate parte of it, muſt be ouerthrowne, the faithfull people of all ages and times, all holy Saintes, all chaſt, all continent, all virgins, all widowes, all Clearkes, all Deacons, all Prieſtes: ſo manie thouſands of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſors, ſo many bands of Martirs, ſo many famous and great cities, and common wealthes, ſo manie Ilandes, Prouinces, Kings, countries, kingdomes, nations, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude almoſt the whole worlde incorporated by the Catholicke faith to Chriſt their heade muſt needs be ſaied, ſo many hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dredes of yeeres to haue bene ignorant, to haue erred, to haue blaſphemed, to haue beleeued they know not what. <hi>Auoide</hi> (quoth he) <hi>Prophane nouelties of voices,</hi> to receiue which, which to folow neuer was the cuſtome of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes, but alwaies the propertie of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes. And to ſay truth, what here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie hath euer peeped forth but vnder the name of ſome certain man in ſome certaine place, and at ſome certaine time. Who euer ſet abroche any he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie?
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19754:47"/> who firſt deuided not him ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the conſent of the vniuerſalitie and antiquitie of the Catholicke Church, which to be true, examples do plainly proue. For who euer before that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane <hi>Pelagius</hi> preſumed ſo much of mans free will that he thought not the grace of God neceſſarie to euery perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer good acte. Who euer before his monſtrous diſciple <hi>Celeſtius</hi> denied all mankind to be tied &amp; bound with the ſinne of <hi>Adams</hi> preuarication? Who euer before ſacriligious <hi>Arius</hi> durſt teare in peeces the Vnitie of Trinitie. Who euer before wicked <hi>Sabellius</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to confound the Trinitie of Vnitie. Who euer before cruell <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </hi> affirmed God to be ſo mercileſſe that he had rather the death of a ſinner then he ſhould returne and liue. Who euer before <hi>Simon Magus</hi> (puniſhed by Apoſtolicall cenſure from whome that olde ſinke of filthines came by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall &amp; ſecrete ſucceſſion vnto <hi>Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillian</hi> that was the laſt) durſt euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that God our Creator was the author of euell, that is the authour of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19754:48"/> our wickednes, impieties, and horrible crimes; becauſe God (as he ſaied) ſo made mans nature that by a certaine proper motion and impulſe of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced will, it can do nothing elſe but ſinne, deſire nothing elſe but to offend, becauſe being prouoked and inflamed with the furious rage of all vices it is with an inſatiable deſire caried away headlong into the pitt and ſincke of all filthines. Such examples are infinite, which for beuitie ſake I omitt, by all which not-withſtanding it appeareth plainly and cleerely that it is an vſuall and common thing in all Hereſies to take great pleaſure in prophane nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to loathe the decrees of our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, and ſo fall from the faith, by oppoſing the falſe &amp; counterfeit name of knowledge and learning: contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe this is proper to all Catholickes to keepe that faith which the holy fathers haue left &amp; committed to their charge to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne prophane nouelties, &amp; as the Apoſtle hath already ſaid &amp; again doth ſay. <hi>Yf any man ſhal preach otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which is receaued to accurſe him.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:19754:48"/>
                     <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
                     <p>HERE haplie ſome man may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde whether heretickes alſo do vſe the teſtimonie of holy ſcripture. To which I ſay that they do and that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie earneſtly, for a man may behold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ranging and courſing in euery parte of the Byble, in <hi>Moyſes,</hi> in the kinges, in the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> in the Apoſtles, in the <hi>Ghoſples,</hi> in the Prophets. for whether they be amongſt their owne bretheren or with ſtrangers: whether in priuate or in publique, whether in talking or in writing, whether in the houſe a fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting or abrode in walking they almoſt neuer alledge any thinge of there owne which they do not pretend to ſhadowe with the wordes of ſacred ſcripture. Read the pamphlets of <hi>Paulus Samo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatenus,</hi> of <hi>Priſcilian Eunomius Iouini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> &amp; the reſt of ſuch like peſtilent He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes, and you ſhall find through all their workes an huge hepe of examples almoſt no page omitted which is not
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19754:49"/> colored and painted with the ſayinges of the new and olde teſtament. But the more cloſely they lurke vnder the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of Gods lawe, the more carefullie are they to be feared the more narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to be watched for they knowe full well that their ſtinking and vnſauorie drugges be not likelie almoſt to pleaſe any, if ſimplie and nakedly they be ſet forth: &amp; therfore they do temper them as it were with the ſweete powder of Gods worde, that he which quicklie would haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temned mans erronious inuention dare not ſo readilie reiecte Gods diuine ſcripture: wherin they are like to thoſe, which minding to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter bitter potions to yonge childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do firſt annoint the brimmes of the cuppe with honie that ther by vnwarie youth feeling the ſwetnes, may nothing feare the bitter confection. This deuiſe alſo practiſe they which vpon noughtie herbes and hurtfull ioyces writte the names of good &amp; wholſome medicines wherby almoſt no man reading the good ſuperſcription, anything ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the lurking poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The ſelfe ſame
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19754:49"/> thing likewiſe our Sauiour crieth out to all Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. <hi>Take ye heed of falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 7</note> 
                        <hi>which come to you in ſheepes cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but inwardly are rauening wolues.</hi> What is ment elſe by ſheepes clothing but the ſayings of the Prophetes and Apoſtles, which they with ſheepelike ſinceritie did weare like certain fleeces for that immaculate Lambe, which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away the ſinnes of the world: And what is to be vnderſtood by rauening wolues, but the cruell &amp; dogged opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of hereticks, which alwaies trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the ſheepfoldes of the Church, and by all meanes poſſible teare in peeces the flocke of Chriſt. But to thend they may more craftely ſet vpon the ſheepe of Chriſt miſtruſting nothing, remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſtill cruell beaſtes, they putt of their woluiſh weed and ſhroude them ſelues with the wordes of ſcripture, as it were with certaine fleeces whereby it hapneth, that when the feelie ſheepe feele the ſoft woll they litle feare their ſharpe teeth: But what ſaieth our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. <hi>By their fruites you ſhall knowe them.</hi> That is when then beginne not
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19754:50"/> only to vtter thoſe wordes, but alſo to expound them, not only to caſt them forth, but alſo to interpret them, then doth that bitternes breake forth, then is that ſharpenes eſpied, then is that madnes perceaued, then is that freſh and new poiſon belched out, then are prophane nouelties ſett abroch, then may you ſee ſtraight way the hedge cut in two, the olde fathers bounds re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, the Cotholicke doctrine ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and the Churches faith torne in peeces. Such were they whome the Apoſtle ſharplie reprehendeth in the 2. epiſtle to the Corinthians: <hi>For ſuch falſe Apoſtles</hi> (quoth he) <hi>are crafty wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11</note> 
                        <hi>transfiguring them ſelues into the Apoſtles of Chriſt.</hi> What is transfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them ſelues into the Apoſtles of Chriſt? But this. The Apoſtles allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the examples of ſcripture, &amp; they likewiſe cited them. The Apoſtles ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the authoritie of the Pſalmes, and they likewiſe vſed it. The Apoſtles v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſayinges of the Prophetes, and they in like maner brought them forth But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſcripture which was alike
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19754:50"/> alleadged, alike cited, alike brought forth, was not alike and in one ſence expounded, then were diſcerned the ſimple from the craftie, the ſincere fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the counterfeit, the right &amp; good from the froward and peruerſe: and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude true Apoſtles from thoſe falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtataes. And no maruell (quoth Saint PAVL) <hi>For Sathan him ſelfe transfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him ſelfe into an Angell of light, it is no great matter therfore if his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters be transfigured as the miniſters of Iuſtice.</hi> Wherfore according to Saint PAVL, whenſoeuer either falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles or falſe Prophets, or falſe Doctors do bring forth the words of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by which they would according to their noughtie interpretation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme their error, there is no doubt but that they folow the craftie ſleight of their maiſter, which ſurely he would neuer haue inuented, but that he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth verie well that there is no readier way to deceaue the people, then where the bringing in of wicked error is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, that there the authoritie of the word of God ſhould be prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. But
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19754:51"/> ſome will ſay how proue you that the Deuill vſeth to alledge ſcripture? Such as doubt therof let them read the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell where it is written. <hi>Then the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill tooke him vp</hi> (that is our Lord and Sauiour) <hi>and ſet him vpon the pinnacle of the Temple, and ſaid vnto him, if thou be the ſonne of God caſt thy ſelfe downe, for it is written that he will geue his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 4</note> 
                        <hi>charge of thee that they may keepe theee in all thy waies, in their hands ſhall they hold the vp, leaſt perhaps thou knock thy foote againſt a ſtone.</hi> How will he thinke you handle ſeely poore ſoules? which ſo ſetteth vpon the Lord of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie with the authoritie of ſcripture. <hi>If thou be</hi> (quoth he) <hi>the ſonne of god caſt thy ſelfe downe.</hi> Why ſo? <hi>For it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </hi> (quoth he). we haue dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to waigh the doctrine of this place &amp; to keepe it in mind that by ſo notable an example of the ſcripture we make no ſcruple or doubt when we ſee any alleadge ſome place of the Apoſtles, or Prophetes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Catholike faith, but that by his mouth the deuil himſelf doth ſpeak. For as at that time the head ſpake vnto
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19754:51"/> the head, ſo now the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers do talke vnto the members, that is the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of the Deuill to the members of Chriſt, the faithleſſe to the faithfull, the irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to the religious, to conclude He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes to Catholickes. But what I pray ſaieth the Deuill? <hi>If thou be the ſonne of God</hi> (quoth he) <hi>caſt thy ſelfe downe.</hi> That is to ſay: Deſireſt thou to be the ſonne of God and to enioy the inheritance of the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Caſt thy ſelfe downe,</hi> that is Caſt thy ſelfe downe from this doctrine &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of this high and loftie Church, which is reputed to be the Temple of God. And if any one demaund of theſe hereticks, perſwading the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch things, how do you proue and conuince me, that I ought to forſake the olde and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall faith of the Catholike Church Straight waies is ready at hand: <hi>For it is written,</hi> &amp; forthwith he will alledge you a thouſand teſtimonies, a thouſand examples, a thouſand authorities out of the law, out of the Pſalmes, out of the Apoſtles, out of the Prophetes, by which expounded after a new &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19754:52"/> faſhion he would throw headlong the vnfortunate ſoules from the tower of the Catholike Church into the deep dungeon of wicked hereſie. Now with theſe ſweete promiſes which followe, Heretickes doe wonderfully deceaue ſimple men. For they dare promiſe and teach that in their Church, that is in the conuenticle of their communion is to be found a great and ſpeciall yea &amp; a certaine perſonall grace of God: So that whoſoeuer be one of their crew, they ſhall ſtraight waies without any labour, without any ſtudy, without any induſtrie yea although they neuer ſeek, nor craue, nor knocke, haue ſuch ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall diſpenſation that they ſhall be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried vp with the handes of Angells, that is preſerued by Angelicall prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: that they neuer hurt their foote againſt a ſtone, that is that they neuer can be ſcandilized. But ſome man wil ſay, if the Deuill &amp; his diſciples, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome be falſe Apoſtles, falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, and falſe teachers, and all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte Heretickes, do vſe the ſcriptures, cite their ſayings, bring forth their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19754:52"/> what ſhall Catholicke men do? How ſhall the children of the Church behaue them ſelues? How ſhall they in the holy ſcriptures diſcerne truth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falſehoode? To which I anſwere that they muſt haue great care (as in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this Treatiſe I ſaid holy and learned men taught me) that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret the diuine and canonicall ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture according to tradition of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Church, according to the rules of the Catholike doctrine: in which like wiſe they muſt of neceſſitie folow, vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſalitie, antiquitie, and conſent, of the Catholicke &amp; Apoſtolike Church. And therefore if at anye time a parte rebell againſt the wholle, noueltie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt antiquitie, the diſſention of one or a few (caried away with error) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the conſent of all, or the farre greater parte of Catholickes: In that caſe let them preferre the integritie of vniuerſalitie before the corruption of a parte: And in vniuerſalitie let them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo preferr the religion of antiquitie be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore prophane noueltie, and againe in antiquitie let them preferre before the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19754:53"/> temeritie of one or a few, the decrees of a generall Councell if any be, or if no ſuch be founde, let them take that which is next hand, that is to followe the opinions of many and great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctors agreeing togither, which faithfully, ſoberly, diligentlye, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and kept: By Gods grace we ſhall without any great difficultie finde out the errors of new vpſtarte Heretickes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XIIII.</head>
                     <p>HERE I perceaue by order it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth to ſhew by exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples how the prophane nouelties of heretickes are by bringing forth and conferring togither the olde Doctors opinions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing togither to be found out and condemned, which auncient conſent of holy fathers is not ſo carefullie and diligently to be ſought for &amp; folowed in euery ſmall queſtion of the ſcripture, but only and eſpecially in the rule of faith, neither yet alwaies, nor all here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies are after this ſorte to be impugned, but only ſuch as be new and vpſtart, to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19754:53"/> wit, at their firſt ſpringing vp &amp; before they haue (lette with lacke of time) fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſified the rules of the auncient faith, &amp; before the poiſon ſpreding far a broad, goeth about to corrupte the Fathers workes: But thoſe hereſies which haue alreadie gott ground, and be of ſome contiunance are not this way to be delt with all, becauſe by long tracte of time they haue had oportunity to ſteal truth And therfore ſuch kinde of prophane ſchiſmes and hereſies which be of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſtanding, we muſt not otherwiſe conuince, but either only if need be, by the authoritie of the ſcriptures, or elſe to auoide and deteſt them being already conuicted and condemned in olde time by generall Councels of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Preiſtes: Therfore ſo ſoon as any infectious error begineth to break forth and for her defence to ſteale cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain words of holy ſcripture, &amp; craftely &amp; fradulently to expound the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſtraight waies for the right vnderſtanding ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Fathers opinions are to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered togither by which let any what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer new, and therfore prophane do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19754:54"/> growing vp with out all delay be deiected and ſpeedely condemned. But thoſe Fathers opinions only are to be conferred togither which with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, wiſdome, and conſtancie, liued, taught, and continued in the faith, and communion of the Catholicke Church and finally deſerued to die in Chriſt or happily for Chriſt to be martired, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding we are to beleeue with this condition, that whatſoeuer either all or the greater parte with one mind, plainly, commonlye, conſtantly, as it were a Councell of Doctors agreeing togither haue decreed and ſet downe receauing it from their aunceſtors, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it for their time, and deliuering it to their poſteritie, let that be had and accounted for vndoubted, for certaine and firme truth (And whatſoeuer any although holy and learned, although a Biſhop, although a Confeſſour, and Martir hath holden otherwiſe then all, or againſt all, let that be put aſide from the authoritie of the common publicke and generall faith &amp; reputed amongſt his owne proper, priuate, and ſecrete
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19754:54"/> opinions, leaſt with greate daunger of eternall ſaluation, we do according to the cuſtome of ſacriligious Heretickes and Schiſmatickes, forſake the trueth of the vniuerſall faith, and follow the nouell error of one man) the holy and and Catholicke mind of which bleſſed Fathers leaſt any man thinke that he may raſhly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temne. The Apoſtle ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.</note> in his firſt epiſtle to the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: <hi>And ſome verely hath God ſet in his Church firſt Apoſtles</hi> of which him ſelf was one: Secondly <hi>Prophetes</hi> as <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> was of whom we read in the Actes. Thirdly <hi>Doctors</hi> which now are called <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cap.</hi> 11.</note> 
                        <hi>Tractators</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo this Apoſtle ſome time nameth Prophetes (becauſe their office was to expound &amp; declare to the people the miſteries of the Prophetes) theſe therfore diſpoſed and placed by God at diuers times and ſundry places, agreeing &amp; conſenting all in one mind in Chriſt, touching the vnderſtanding of the Catholicke faith whoſoeuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temneth, doth not contemne man but God: and that we diſagree not by any meanes from the perfect and true vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19754:55"/> of thoſe Fathers, the ſame Apoſtle doth earneſtly beſeech all Chriſtians, ſaying: <hi>I beſeech you brethren that you ſay all one thing and that there bee no ſchiſmes among you, but that you be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1</note> 
                        <hi>in one ſence and in one knowledge.</hi> And if any man ſeparate him ſelfe from the communion of theire opinion, let him heare that ſaying of the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: <hi>He is not the God of diſſention but</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14</note> 
                        <hi>of peace:</hi> that is not of him that leaueth conſent and vnitie, but of them that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in peace and agreement: <hi>As I do</hi> (quoth he) <hi>teach in all the Churches of the Saintes,</hi> that is of Catholickes, which therfore be holy becauſe they continue in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the faith: and leaſt happily any one ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne others and proudly require only to be heard, only to be beleeued, ſtrait after he ſaieth. <hi>What hath the word of God</hi> (quoth he) <hi>proceeded from you or haue it only come to you.</hi> And leaſt this might be taken as ſpoken ſlightlye he addeth. <hi>If any</hi> (quoth he) <hi>ſeemeh a Prophet or ſpirituall,</hi> that is a maſter in ſpirituall matters, let him be a zealous
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19754:55"/> louer of vnitie and peace, in ſuch wiſe that he neither preferre his owne opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion before the iudgement of others, neither leaue or forſake the ſence and common conſent of all men. <hi>The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes of which thinges he that is</hi> (quoth he) <hi>ignorant of:</hi> that is he that learneth not thoſe thinges which he yet knoweth not, or contemneth thoſe which he knoweth, <hi>he ſhal not be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that is he ſhall be thought vnworthie, whom amongeſt ſuch, as be vnited in faith &amp; equall in humilitie God ſhould regard and looke vpon: a greater euill then which I doubt whether any man can inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or deuiſe which yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding (accordinge to the Apoſtles commination) wee ſee to haue fallen vpon <hi>Iultan</hi> the <hi>Pelagian</hi> who either conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned to be ioined in opinion with his felowes or elſe preſumed to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate him ſelfe from theire ſocietie and communion.</p>
                     <p>But now it is time to bring forth the example which we promiſed: how and after what ſort the iudgement and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of holy Fathers were gathered
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19754:56"/> togither, that according to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the decree and authority of a Councell the rule of faith might be ſet down: which to the end that I may more commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly do, I will here make an end of this commonitorie and ſo take a nother be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning for declaring of thoſe thinges which do folow and enſew.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="summary">
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:19754:56"/>
                     <head>A RECAPITVLATION of all that hath bene ſaid in the former two bookes.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HICH being ſo it is now time that in the ende of this ſecond booke we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capitulate &amp; touch in few wordes the Summe of all that which in theſe two commonitorie bookes hath bene ſpoken. We ſaied in the premiſſes that this alwaies hath bene and at this day is the cuſtome of Catholickes to try and examine true faith two manner of waies. Firſt by the authoritie of the deuine ſcripture: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly by the tradition of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church, not becauſe the Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſcripture is not of it ſelfe ſufficient for all thinges, but becauſe verie many expounding Gods word at there owne
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19754:57"/> pleaſure, doe thereby bring forth and hatch vp diuers opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; errors. And for that cauſe it is neceſſarie that the interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the diuine ſcripture be directed according to the one onely rule of the Churches vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in thoſe queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vpon which the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the whole Catholicke religion doth depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Likewiſe we ſaid that in the Church we had to conſider the conſent both of vniuerſalitie and antiquitie, ſo that we be neither caried a way from ſound vnitie to ſchiſme nor yet caſt headlong fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> antiquitie of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion into the daungerous gulfe of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall nouelties. We ſaid alſo that in antiquity we had diligently to obſerue and ſeriouſly to conſider two thinges, vnto which all thoſe that will not bee heretickes muſt of neceſſitie ſtand. The firſt is, that which hath in oulde time bene determined by all the biſhopes of the Catholicke Church by authority of a generall Councell. The ſecond is that if any new queſtion did ariſe in which the determination of a Councell were not to be found that then we ought to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19754:57"/> haue recourſe to the ſayings of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers, but yet of theſe only who in theire time and place were probable maiſters, being ſuch as liued and died in the vnitie of the communion and faith. And whatſoeuer we knew that they beleeued &amp; taught with one mind and conſente to iudge and take that without all ſcruple to be the true and Catholicke Religion of the Church.</p>
                     <p>And leaſt any man might think that we ſaied this rather of preſumption the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any authoritie of the Church, we gaue an example of the holy Councell holden almoſt three yeeres ſithence at <hi>Epheſus</hi> a Citie in <hi>Aſia</hi> in the time of the right honorable Councels <hi>Baſſus</hi> &amp; <hi>Antiochus,</hi> in which diſputation was had of conſtituting and ſetting downe rules of faith: and leaſt there might by chance ſome prophane Noueltie creep in, as happened at that perſidious mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in <hi>Ariminum</hi> this was reputed and thought the moſt Catholicke, holy, &amp; beſt courſe to be taken, by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the Biſhops there preſent, which were almoſt two hundred in
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19754:58"/> number: that the opinions of theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhould be brought forth of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was certaine that ſome of them had bene Martirs, diuerſe Confeſſors, and all to haue liued and died Catholicke Preiſts that by their authoritie, conſent and verdict, the old religion might be rightlie and ſolemnely confirmed, and blaſphemous prophane nouelties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, which being ſo done worthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and iuſtlie, <hi>Neſtorius</hi> was iudged to haue taught contrary to the old Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and bleſſed <hi>Cirill</hi> to haue maintained holy and ſacred antiquitie. And to the end nothing might be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting which procureth credite we put downe alſo the names and number of theſe Fathers (although not reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring their order) according to whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and vniforme doctrine both the textes of holy ſcripture were expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the rule of Gods word eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Neither will it here be ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for memory ſake to repeate them all once againe. Theſe then bee the names of them, whoſe workes were cited in that Councell either as iudges
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19754:58"/> or elſe as witneſſes. <hi>S. Peter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> a moſt excellent Doctor and bleſſed Martir. <hi>S. Athanaſius</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhope of the ſame ſea a moſt faithfull teacher and famous Confeſſor. <hi>S. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophilus</hi> Biſhope alſo of the ſame Citie, a notable man for faith, life and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, next after whom ſucceded vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Cirill,</hi> who at this preſent doth honour the Church of <hi>Alexandria.</hi> And that no man happelie ſhould ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecte that this was the doctrine of one Citie or of one Prouince: to the former there were adioined thoſe two lightes of <hi>Caperdocia</hi> Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> Biſhoppe and Confeſſor of <hi>Nazianzene</hi> &amp; Saint <hi>Baſill</hi> Biſhope and Confeſſor of <hi>Ceſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi> &amp; alſo another Saint <hi>Gregory Niſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen</hi> worthy for his merite of faith, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, integritie, and wiſdome of ſuch a brother as <hi>Baſill</hi> was. And for proofe that not onely the greeke and Eaſte Church, but alſo the Latin, and Weaſt, were alwaies of the ſame opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, the letters of Saint <hi>Felix</hi> Martir and Saint <hi>Iulie</hi> both Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> which they wrote vnto certaine men
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19754:59"/> were there read. And that not onely the head of the world but alſo the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther partes ſhould giue teſtimonie in that iudgement. From the South they had bleſſed S. <hi>Ciprian,</hi> from the North S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Millan.</hi> Theſe then be the holy Fathers agreeing with that ſacred number of the tenne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements which were alleadged in the Councell of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> as Maſters, Councellors, Witneſſes, and Iudges, whoſe doctrine the bleſſed <hi>Synod</hi> hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, following whoſe counſaile, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuinge whoſe teſtimonie, obeyinge whoſe iudgement, without ſpite, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preſumption, and without fauour, pronounced &amp; gaue ſentence concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the rules of faith. And albeit a farre greater number of Fathers might haue bene ſet downe, yet was it not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, becauſe it was not requiſite that time ſhould be ſpent with multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of witneſſes: and further no man doubted but that thoſe tenne did litle differ in opinion from all the reſt of their fellow Biſhopes. After all this we ſett downe the worthie ſentence of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:19754:59"/> 
                        <hi>Cirill</hi> which is to be found in the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall actes of that Councell. For when the epiſtle of <hi>S. Capreolus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage</hi> was reade, who intended nothing elſe, nothing elſe deſired, but that noueltie might be ouer throwen, &amp; antiquitie defended, Biſhope <hi>Cirill</hi> ſpake and gaue his definition in this ſort: for I haue thought good not to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt it here: theſe then be his wordes in the end of the actes of that Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell. <hi>And this epiſtle</hi> (quoth he) <hi>of the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and religious man Capreolus Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhope of Carthage ſhall be adioyned to the faith of the Councels actes, whoſe opinion is plaine and perſpicuous, for he deſireth that the dostrine of the olde faith may be confirmed and new opinions ſuperfluouſly inuented &amp; impiouſly ſpread a brode may be reproued and condemned.</hi> To which all the Biſhopes with one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent cried out. This we ſpake all, this we teach all, this we deſire all: what I beſeech you ſaied they all, what deſired they all? ſurely nothing elſe but that which was of olde time deliuered, might be ſtill retained: and that which was newlie
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19754:60"/> inuented might ſpeedelie be reiected. After all which we maruailed at and highly commended the greate humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and holines of that Councell, in which were ſo many Biſhopes, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of whom were almoſt <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politanes,</hi> of ſuch eruditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of ſuch lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that they were almoſt all ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to haue diſputed of matters of faith Which greate aſſemblie and meeting together although it might in ſome mans opinion haue imboldened them to preſume and determine ſomwhat of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, yet they deliuered nothing, preſumed nothing, arrogated nothing to themſelues, but before all thinges they were very carefull not to leaue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to poſteritie, which before they had not receiued of their forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: not thinking it ſufficient to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe well of the buſineſſe then preſent but alſo to leaue an example to their poſteritie, how they in like manner ſhould reuerence the religion of ſacred antiquitie, and vtterly condemne the inuentions of prophane noueltie. We inuaighed alſo againſt the wicked pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:19754:60"/> of <hi>Neſtorius</hi> who boaſted that he was the firſt and the only man which vnderſtood the ſcriptures, and that all others which before his daies preached and taught, all that interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and expounded the word of God were ignorant and vnskilfull, that is all Preiſtes, all Confeſſors and Martirs, of whom ſome had expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Gods lawe others allowed and beleeued them. To conclude he maintained that the Church both now did erre and alwaies had erred, becauſe as he thought it had and did folow vnlearned and erronious Doctors: All which albeit they were abundantly ſufficient for the ouertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; extinguiſhing of all prophane nouelties. Yet leaſt that ought ſhold in ſuch ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie of proofes be wanting, we added for a concluſion a doble autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Sea Apoſtolique, the one of holy <hi>Pope Xiſtus</hi> which venerable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nowe honoureth the Church of Rome, the other of <hi>Pope Celeſtinus</hi> of bleſſed memorie his prediceſſor which I haue thought good alſo here to ſett downe. <hi>Pope Xiſtus</hi> then in his epiſtle
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:19754:61"/> which he wrot to the Biſhope of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch</hi> towching the cauſe of <hi>Neſtorius</hi> ſaieth thus. <hi>Therfore</hi> (quoth he) <hi>becauſe</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaieth <hi>the faith is one which euidently hath obtained to be ſo called let vs beleeue, and ſuch thinges as are to bee holden lett vs beleeue.</hi> After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he proſecuteth and explicateth what thoſe thinges be which are to be beleeued, what they be which are to be kept, ſaying thus: <hi>Nothing</hi> (quoth he) <hi>is further lawefull for Noueltie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient that nothing be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to Antiquitie. The faith &amp; beleefe of our forefathers is cleare &amp; perſpicuous let it not be troubled or defiled with any permixtion of filthie mire.</hi> Apoſtolically ſpoken: in commendation of our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers faith, to compare it to light and perſpicuitie, and in likening nouell pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes to the admixtion of filth and mire. <hi>Pope Celeſtinus</hi> likewiſe is of the ſame opinion, for in his epiſtle which he ſent to the Preiſtes of <hi>France,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he reprehendeth their diſſimulation in that they left by their ſilence the old faith deſtitute, and ſuffered prophane
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19754:61"/> Nouelties to ſpring vp, thus he writeth <hi>Worthelie</hi> (quoth hee) <hi>the cauſe doth touch vs if with ſilence we foſter errour therfore let ſuch men be corrected, let them haue no libertie to ſpeake at their pleaſure.</hi> Some happely doubteth who they be, whom he forbiddeth to haue their libertie in ſpeaking, whether the preachers of antiquitie, or the inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of nouelties: Let him ſpeake and diſcharge the Reader of this doubt, for it foloweth: <hi>Let nouelty ceaſe of</hi> (quoth he) <hi>if the matter be ſo:</hi> that is if that be true which diuers accuſe vnto me your Cities &amp; Prouinces that through your pernitious diſſimulation you cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to yeeld vnto certaine new doctrine: <hi>Therfore</hi> (quoth he) <hi>if the matter be ſo, let noueltie ceaſe of to prouoke Antiquity</hi> This then was the bleſſed opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Celeſtinus,</hi> not that antiquity ſhould ceaſe to ouerthrow Noueltie, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Noueltie ſhould giue ouer to prouoke antiquitie: Which Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke and Catholicke decrees, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer reſiſteth firſt of neceſſitie he muſt proudly contemne the memorie of S.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19754:62"/> 
                        <hi>Celeſtinus</hi> who defined that noueltie ſhould giue ouer to prouoke antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Againe he muſtieſt &amp; ſcoffe at the decree of holy <hi>Xiſtus,</hi> whoſe iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is, that nothing is lawfull for noueltie, becauſe it is not conuenient that ought be added to antiquitie. Againe he muſt contemne the determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of bleſſed <hi>Cirill,</hi> who highlie commended the zeale of venerable <hi>Capreolus,</hi> in that he deſired, that the old articles of faith ſhould be confirmed &amp; new inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions vtterly condemned. Likewiſe he muſt reiect the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> that is the iudgement almoſt of all the holy Biſhopes of the Eaſt, who inſpired by God would not decree that poſteritie ſhould beleeue ought but that which the ſacred antiquitie of our forefathers agreeing togither in Chriſt had holden &amp; beleeued, who with their vniforme allowing &amp; acclamation teſtified that they all decreed, all wiſhed, all gaue iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that is all heretickes almoſt before <hi>Neſtorius</hi> contemning antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and defending Noueltie were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned. So likewiſe <hi>Neſtorius</hi> him ſelfe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:19754:62"/> the author of noueltie and impugner of antiquitie ſhould bee condemned. Whoſe ſacred conſent and agreement proceding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods goodnes if any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, what remaineth but that he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that <hi>Neſtorius</hi> prophane opinion was vniuſtly condemned. Finally hee muſt alſo ſett light by, and contemne the vniuerſall Church of Chriſt, and her maſters the Apoſtles and Prophetes, and eſpecially the Apoſtle <hi>S.</hi> PAVL, as dreggs &amp; droſſe. The vniuerſal Church beecauſe ſhee hath alwaies religiouſly kepte and maintained that faith which was once deliuered S. PAVL, becauſe he hath written thus. <hi>O Timothy keepe the depoſitum auoiding prophane Nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of voices.</hi> And againe. <hi>Yf any preach vnto you otherwiſe then you haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued bee he accurſed.</hi> And if neither the Apoſtle his definition nor the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ought to be violated, by which according to the ſacred con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of vniuerſalitie and antiquitie, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies all heretickes, and laſtlie <hi>Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius Celeſtius</hi> and <hi>Neſtorius</hi> were iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and worthelie condemned, ſurelie
<pb facs="tcp:19754:63"/> neceſſarie it is that hereafter all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes which deſire to ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues true childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their mother the church doe cleaue, ioine, and ſticke vnto the holy faith of their holy Fathers dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and abhorring, purſueing &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the prophane nouelties of all prophane miſereantes. This almoſt is the ſumme of that which in theſe two commonitorie bookes we haue more amplie diſcourſed of, &amp; now after the maner of recapitulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in fewer words gathered togither that my memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for helpinge whereof I haue wrote this Treatiſe may both with dailye admonition be repaired, and yet not ouerlaid with faſtidious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixitie.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
